<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="manual-core" xreflabel="Valgrind's core">
<title>Using and understanding the Valgrind core</title>

<para>This section describes the Valgrind core services, flags
and behaviours.  That means it is relevant regardless of what
particular tool you are using.  A point of terminology: most
references to "valgrind" in the rest of this section (Section 2)
refer to the valgrind core services.</para>

<sect1 id="manual-core.whatdoes" 
       xreflabel="What Valgrind does with your program">
<title>What Valgrind does with your program</title>

<para>Valgrind is designed to be as non-intrusive as possible. It
works directly with existing executables. You don't need to
recompile, relink, or otherwise modify, the program to be
checked.</para>

<para>Simply put <computeroutput>valgrind
--tool=tool_name</computeroutput> at the start of the command
line normally used to run the program.  For example, if want to
run the command <computeroutput>ls -l</computeroutput> using the
heavyweight memory-checking tool Memcheck, issue the
command:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
valgrind --tool=memcheck ls -l]]></programlisting>

<para>(Memcheck is the default, so if you want to use it you can
actually omit the <computeroutput>--tool</computeroutput> flag.</para>

<para>Regardless of which tool is in use, Valgrind takes control
of your program before it starts.  Debugging information is read
from the executable and associated libraries, so that error
messages and other outputs can be phrased in terms of source code
locations (if that is appropriate).</para>

<para>Your program is then run on a synthetic CPU provided by
the Valgrind core.  As new code is executed for the first time,
the core hands the code to the selected tool.  The tool adds its
own instrumentation code to this and hands the result back to the
core, which coordinates the continued execution of this
instrumented code.</para>

<para>The amount of instrumentation code added varies widely
between tools.  At one end of the scale, Memcheck adds code to
check every memory access and every value computed, increasing
the size of the code at least 12 times, and making it run 25-50
times slower than natively.  At the other end of the spectrum,
the ultra-trivial "none" tool (a.k.a. Nulgrind) adds no
instrumentation at all and causes in total "only" about a 4 times
slowdown.</para>

<para>Valgrind simulates every single instruction your program
executes.  Because of this, the active tool checks, or profiles,
not only the code in your application but also in all supporting
dynamically-linked (<computeroutput>.so</computeroutput>-format)
libraries, including the GNU C library, the X client libraries,
Qt, if you work with KDE, and so on.</para>

<para>If you're using one of the error-detection tools, Valgrind
will often detect errors in libraries, for example the GNU C or
X11 libraries, which you have to use.  You might not be
interested in these errors, since you probably have no control
over that code.  Therefore, Valgrind allows you to selectively
suppress errors, by recording them in a suppressions file which
is read when Valgrind starts up.  The build mechanism attempts to
select suppressions which give reasonable behaviour for the libc
and XFree86 versions detected on your machine.  To make it easier
to write suppressions, you can use the
<computeroutput>--gen-suppressions=yes</computeroutput> option
which tells Valgrind to print out a suppression for each error
that appears, which you can then copy into a suppressions
file.</para>

<para>Different error-checking tools report different kinds of
errors.  The suppression mechanism therefore allows you to say
which tool or tool(s) each suppression applies to.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.started" xreflabel="Getting started">
<title>Getting started</title>

<para>First off, consider whether it might be beneficial to
recompile your application and supporting libraries with
debugging info enabled (the <computeroutput>-g</computeroutput>
flag).  Without debugging info, the best Valgrind tools will be
able to do is guess which function a particular piece of code
belongs to, which makes both error messages and profiling output
nearly useless.  With <computeroutput>-g</computeroutput>, you'll
hopefully get messages which point directly to the relevant
source code lines.</para>

<para>Another flag you might like to consider, if you are working
with C++, is <computeroutput>-fno-inline</computeroutput>.  That
makes it easier to see the function-call chain, which can help
reduce confusion when navigating around large C++ apps.  For
whatever it's worth, debugging OpenOffice.org with Memcheck is a
bit easier when using this flag.</para>

<para>You don't have to do this, but doing so helps Valgrind
produce more accurate and less confusing error reports.  Chances
are you're set up like this already, if you intended to debug
your program with GNU gdb, or some other debugger.</para>

<para>This paragraph applies only if you plan to use Memcheck: On
rare occasions, optimisation levels at
<computeroutput>-O2</computeroutput> and above have been observed
to generate code which fools Memcheck into wrongly reporting
uninitialised value errors.  We have looked in detail into fixing
this, and unfortunately the result is that doing so would give a
further significant slowdown in what is already a slow tool.  So
the best solution is to turn off optimisation altogether.  Since
this often makes things unmanagably slow, a plausible compromise
is to use <computeroutput>-O</computeroutput>.  This gets you the
majority of the benefits of higher optimisation levels whilst
keeping relatively small the chances of false complaints from
Memcheck.  All other tools (as far as we know) are unaffected by
optimisation level.</para>

<para>Valgrind understands both the older "stabs" debugging
format, used by gcc versions prior to 3.1, and the newer DWARF2
format used by gcc 3.1 and later.  We continue to refine and
debug our debug-info readers, although the majority of effort
will naturally enough go into the newer DWARF2 reader.</para>

<para>When you're ready to roll, just run your application as you
would normally, but place <computeroutput>valgrind
--tool=tool_name</computeroutput> in front of your usual
command-line invocation.  Note that you should run the real
(machine-code) executable here.  If your application is started
by, for example, a shell or perl script, you'll need to modify it
to invoke Valgrind on the real executables.  Running such scripts
directly under Valgrind will result in you getting error reports
pertaining to <computeroutput>/bin/sh</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>/usr/bin/perl</computeroutput>, or whatever
interpreter you're using.  This may not be what you want and can
be confusing.  You can force the issue by giving the flag
<computeroutput>--trace-children=yes</computeroutput>, but
confusion is still likely.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.comment" xreflabel="The commentary">
<title>The commentary</title>

<para>Valgrind tools write a commentary, a stream of text,
detailing error reports and other significant events.  All lines
in the commentary have following form:

<programlisting><![CDATA[
==12345== some-message-from-Valgrind]]></programlisting>
</para>

<para>The <computeroutput>12345</computeroutput> is the process
ID.  This scheme makes it easy to distinguish program output from
Valgrind commentary, and also easy to differentiate commentaries
from different processes which have become merged together, for
whatever reason.</para>

<para>By default, Valgrind tools write only essential messages to
the commentary, so as to avoid flooding you with information of
secondary importance.  If you want more information about what is
happening, re-run, passing the
<computeroutput>-v</computeroutput> flag to Valgrind.</para>

<para>You can direct the commentary to three different
places:</para>

<orderedlist>

 <listitem id="manual-core.out2fd" xreflabel="Directing output to fd">
   <para>The default: send it to a file descriptor, which is by
   default 2 (stderr).  So, if you give the core no options, it
   will write commentary to the standard error stream.  If you
   want to send it to some other file descriptor, for example
   number 9, you can specify
   <computeroutput>--log-fd=9</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="manual-core.out2file" 
            xreflabel="Directing output to file">
   <para>A less intrusive option is to write the commentary to a
   file, which you specify by
   <computeroutput>--log-file=filename</computeroutput>.  Note
   carefully that the commentary is <command>not</command>
   written to the file you specify, but instead to one called
   <computeroutput>filename.pid12345</computeroutput>, if for
   example the pid of the traced process is 12345.  This is
   helpful when valgrinding a whole tree of processes at once,
   since it means that each process writes to its own logfile,
   rather than the result being jumbled up in one big
   logfile.  If <computeroutput>filename.pid12345</computeroutput> already
   exists, then it will name new files
   <computeroutput>filename.pid12345.1</computeroutput> and so on.
   </para>

   <para>If you want to specify precisely the file name to use,
   without the trailing
   <computeroutput>.pid12345</computeroutput>part, you can instead use
   <computeroutput>--log-file-exactly=filename</computeroutput>.
   </para>

   <para>You can also use the
   <computeroutput>--log-file-qualifier=&lt;VAR&gt;</computeroutput> option
   to specify the filename via the environment variable
   <computeroutput>$VAR</computeroutput>.  This is rarely needed, but
   very useful in certain circumstances (eg. when running MPI programs).
   </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="manual-core.out2socket" 
            xreflabel="Directing output to network socket">
   <para>The least intrusive option is to send the commentary to
   a network socket.  The socket is specified as an IP address
   and port number pair, like this:
   <computeroutput>--log-socket=192.168.0.1:12345</computeroutput>
   if you want to send the output to host IP 192.168.0.1 port
   12345 (I have no idea if 12345 is a port of pre-existing
   significance).  You can also omit the port number:
   <computeroutput>--log-socket=192.168.0.1</computeroutput>, in
   which case a default port of 1500 is used.  This default is
   defined by the constant
   <computeroutput>VG_CLO_DEFAULT_LOGPORT</computeroutput> in the
   sources.</para>

   <para>Note, unfortunately, that you have to use an IP address
   here, rather than a hostname.</para>

   <para>Writing to a network socket is pretty useless if you
   don't have something listening at the other end.  We provide a
   simple listener program,
   <computeroutput>valgrind-listener</computeroutput>, which
   accepts connections on the specified port and copies whatever
   it is sent to stdout.  Probably someone will tell us this is a
   horrible security risk.  It seems likely that people will
   write more sophisticated listeners in the fullness of
   time.</para>

   <para>valgrind-listener can accept simultaneous connections
   from up to 50 valgrinded processes.  In front of each line of
   output it prints the current number of active connections in
   round brackets.</para>

   <para>valgrind-listener accepts two command-line flags:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para><computeroutput>-e</computeroutput> or 
      <computeroutput>--exit-at-zero</computeroutput>: when the
      number of connected processes falls back to zero, exit.
      Without this, it will run forever, that is, until you send
      it Control-C.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para><computeroutput>portnumber</computeroutput>: changes
      the port it listens on from the default (1500).  The
      specified port must be in the range 1024 to 65535.  The
      same restriction applies to port numbers specified by a
      <computeroutput>--log-socket=</computeroutput> to Valgrind
      itself.</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>If a valgrinded process fails to connect to a listener,
    for whatever reason (the listener isn't running, invalid or
    unreachable host or port, etc), Valgrind switches back to
    writing the commentary to stderr.  The same goes for any
    process which loses an established connection to a listener.
    In other words, killing the listener doesn't kill the
    processes sending data to it.</para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

<para>Here is an important point about the relationship between
the commentary and profiling output from tools.  The commentary
contains a mix of messages from the Valgrind core and the
selected tool.  If the tool reports errors, it will report them
to the commentary.  However, if the tool does profiling, the
profile data will be written to a file of some kind, depending on
the tool, and independent of what
<computeroutput>--log-*</computeroutput> options are in force.
The commentary is intended to be a low-bandwidth, human-readable
channel.  Profiling data, on the other hand, is usually
voluminous and not meaningful without further processing, which
is why we have chosen this arrangement.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.report" xreflabel="Reporting of errors">
<title>Reporting of errors</title>

<para>When one of the error-checking tools (Memcheck, Addrcheck,
Helgrind) detects something bad happening in the program, an
error message is written to the commentary.  For example:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
==25832== Invalid read of size 4
==25832==    at 0x8048724: BandMatrix::ReSize(int, int, int) (bogon.cpp:45)
==25832==    by 0x80487AF: main (bogon.cpp:66)
==25832==  Address 0xBFFFF74C is not stack'd, malloc'd or free'd]]></programlisting>

<para>This message says that the program did an illegal 4-byte
read of address 0xBFFFF74C, which, as far as Memcheck can tell,
is not a valid stack address, nor corresponds to any currently
malloc'd or free'd blocks.  The read is happening at line 45 of
<filename>bogon.cpp</filename>, called from line 66 of the same
file, etc.  For errors associated with an identified
malloc'd/free'd block, for example reading free'd memory,
Valgrind reports not only the location where the error happened,
but also where the associated block was malloc'd/free'd.</para>

<para>Valgrind remembers all error reports.  When an error is
detected, it is compared against old reports, to see if it is a
duplicate.  If so, the error is noted, but no further commentary
is emitted.  This avoids you being swamped with bazillions of
duplicate error reports.</para>

<para>If you want to know how many times each error occurred, run
with the <computeroutput>-v</computeroutput> option.  When
execution finishes, all the reports are printed out, along with,
and sorted by, their occurrence counts.  This makes it easy to
see which errors have occurred most frequently.</para>

<para>Errors are reported before the associated operation
actually happens.  If you're using a tool (Memcheck, Addrcheck)
which does address checking, and your program attempts to read
from address zero, the tool will emit a message to this effect,
and the program will then duly die with a segmentation
fault.</para>

<para>In general, you should try and fix errors in the order that
they are reported.  Not doing so can be confusing.  For example,
a program which copies uninitialised values to several memory
locations, and later uses them, will generate several error
messages, when run on Memcheck.  The first such error message may
well give the most direct clue to the root cause of the
problem.</para>

<para>The process of detecting duplicate errors is quite an
expensive one and can become a significant performance overhead
if your program generates huge quantities of errors.  To avoid
serious problems here, Valgrind will simply stop collecting
errors after 300 different errors have been seen, or 30000 errors
in total have been seen.  In this situation you might as well
stop your program and fix it, because Valgrind won't tell you
anything else useful after this.  Note that the 300/30000 limits
apply after suppressed errors are removed.  These limits are
defined in <filename>m_errormgr.c</filename> and can be increased
if necessary.</para>

<para>To avoid this cutoff you can use the
<computeroutput>--error-limit=no</computeroutput> flag.  Then
Valgrind will always show errors, regardless of how many there
are.  Use this flag carefully, since it may have a dire effect on
performance.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.suppress" xreflabel="Suppressing errors">
<title>Suppressing errors</title>

<para>The error-checking tools detect numerous problems in the
base libraries, such as the GNU C library, and the XFree86 client
libraries, which come pre-installed on your GNU/Linux system.
You can't easily fix these, but you don't want to see these
errors (and yes, there are many!)  So Valgrind reads a list of
errors to suppress at startup.  A default suppression file is
cooked up by the <computeroutput>./configure</computeroutput>
script when the system is built.</para>

<para>You can modify and add to the suppressions file at your
leisure, or, better, write your own.  Multiple suppression files
are allowed.  This is useful if part of your project contains
errors you can't or don't want to fix, yet you don't want to
continuously be reminded of them.</para>

<formalpara><title>Note:</title>
<para>By far the easiest way to add suppressions is to use the
<computeroutput>--gen-suppressions=yes</computeroutput> flag
described in <xref linkend="manual-core.flags"/>.</para>
</formalpara>

<para>Each error to be suppressed is described very specifically,
to minimise the possibility that a suppression-directive
inadvertantly suppresses a bunch of similar errors which you did
want to see.  The suppression mechanism is designed to allow
precise yet flexible specification of errors to suppress.</para>

<para>If you use the <computeroutput>-v</computeroutput> flag, at
the end of execution, Valgrind prints out one line for each used
suppression, giving its name and the number of times it got used.
Here's the suppressions used by a run of <computeroutput>valgrind
--tool=memcheck ls -l</computeroutput>:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
--27579-- supp: 1 socketcall.connect(serv_addr)/__libc_connect/__nscd_getgrgid_r
--27579-- supp: 1 socketcall.connect(serv_addr)/__libc_connect/__nscd_getpwuid_r
--27579-- supp: 6 strrchr/_dl_map_object_from_fd/_dl_map_object]]></programlisting>

<para>Multiple suppressions files are allowed.  By default,
Valgrind uses
<computeroutput>$PREFIX/lib/valgrind/default.supp</computeroutput>.
You can ask to add suppressions from another file, by specifying
<computeroutput>--suppressions=/path/to/file.supp</computeroutput>.
</para>

<para>If you want to understand more about suppressions, look at
an existing suppressions file whilst reading the following
documentation.  The file
<computeroutput>glibc-2.2.supp</computeroutput>, in the source
distribution, provides some good examples.</para>

<para>Each suppression has the following components:</para>

 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
   <para>First line: its name.  This merely gives a handy name to
   the suppression, by which it is referred to in the summary of
   used suppressions printed out when a program finishes.  It's
   not important what the name is; any identifying string will
   do.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Second line: name of the tool(s) that the suppression is
   for (if more than one, comma-separated), and the name of the
   suppression itself, separated by a colon (Nb: no spaces are
   allowed), eg:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
tool_name1,tool_name2:suppression_name]]></programlisting>

   <para>Recall that Valgrind-2.0.X is a modular system, in which
   different instrumentation tools can observe your program
   whilst it is running.  Since different tools detect different
   kinds of errors, it is necessary to say which tool(s) the
   suppression is meaningful to.</para>

   <para>Tools will complain, at startup, if a tool does not
   understand any suppression directed to it.  Tools ignore
   suppressions which are not directed to them.  As a result, it
   is quite practical to put suppressions for all tools into the
   same suppression file.</para>

   <para>Valgrind's core can detect certain PThreads API errors,
   for which this line reads:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
core:PThread]]></programlisting>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Next line: a small number of suppression types have
   extra information after the second line (eg. the
   <computeroutput>Param</computeroutput> suppression for
   Memcheck)</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Remaining lines: This is the calling context for the
   error -- the chain of function calls that led to it.  There
   can be up to four of these lines.</para>

   <para>Locations may be either names of shared
   objects/executables or wildcards matching function names.
   They begin <computeroutput>obj:</computeroutput> and
   <computeroutput>fun:</computeroutput> respectively.  Function
   and object names to match against may use the wildcard
   characters <computeroutput>*</computeroutput> and
   <computeroutput>?</computeroutput>.</para>

   <formalpara><title>Important note:</title>
    <para>C++ function names must be <command>mangled</command>.
    If you are writing suppressions by hand, use the
    <computeroutput>--demangle=no</computeroutput> option to get
    the mangled names in your error messages.</para>
   </formalpara>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Finally, the entire suppression must be between curly
   braces. Each brace must be the first character on its own
   line.</para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>

<para>A suppression only suppresses an error when the error
matches all the details in the suppression.  Here's an
example:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
{
  __gconv_transform_ascii_internal/__mbrtowc/mbtowc
  Memcheck:Value4
  fun:__gconv_transform_ascii_internal
  fun:__mbr*toc
  fun:mbtowc
}]]></programlisting>


<para>What it means is: for Memcheck only, suppress a
use-of-uninitialised-value error, when the data size is 4, when
it occurs in the function
<computeroutput>__gconv_transform_ascii_internal</computeroutput>,
when that is called from any function of name matching
<computeroutput>__mbr*toc</computeroutput>, when that is called
from <computeroutput>mbtowc</computeroutput>.  It doesn't apply
under any other circumstances.  The string by which this
suppression is identified to the user is
<computeroutput>__gconv_transform_ascii_internal/__mbrtowc/mbtowc</computeroutput>.</para>

<para>(See <xref linkend="mc-manual.suppfiles"/> for more details
on the specifics of Memcheck's suppression kinds.)</para>

<para>Another example, again for the Memcheck tool:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
{
  libX11.so.6.2/libX11.so.6.2/libXaw.so.7.0
  Memcheck:Value4
  obj:/usr/X11R6/lib/libX11.so.6.2
  obj:/usr/X11R6/lib/libX11.so.6.2
  obj:/usr/X11R6/lib/libXaw.so.7.0
}]]></programlisting>

<para>Suppress any size 4 uninitialised-value error which occurs
anywhere in <computeroutput>libX11.so.6.2</computeroutput>, when
called from anywhere in the same library, when called from
anywhere in <computeroutput>libXaw.so.7.0</computeroutput>.  The
inexact specification of locations is regrettable, but is about
all you can hope for, given that the X11 libraries shipped with
Red Hat 7.2 have had their symbol tables removed.</para>

<para>Note: since the above two examples did not make it clear,
you can freely mix the <computeroutput>obj:</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>fun:</computeroutput> styles of description
within a single suppression record.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.flags" 
       xreflabel="Command-line flags for the Valgrind core">
<title>Command-line flags for the Valgrind core</title>

<para>As mentioned above, Valgrind's core accepts a common set of
flags.  The tools also accept tool-specific flags, which are
documented seperately for each tool.</para>

<para>You invoke Valgrind like this:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
valgrind --tool=<emphasis>tool_name</emphasis> [valgrind-options] your-prog [your-prog options]]]></programlisting>

<para>Valgrind's default settings succeed in giving reasonable
behaviour in most cases.  We group the available options by rough
categories.</para>

<sect2 id="manual-core.toolopts" xreflabel="Tool-selection option">
<title>Tool-selection option</title>

<para>The single most important option.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem id="tool_name">
    <para><computeroutput>--tool=name</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Run the Valgrind tool called <emphasis>name</emphasis>,
    e.g. Memcheck, Addrcheck, Cachegrind, etc.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="manual-core.basicopts" xreflabel="Basic Options">
<title>Basic Options</title>

<para>These options work with all tools.</para>

 <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>--help</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Show help for all options, both for the core and for
    the selected tool.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>--help-debug</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Same as <computeroutput>--help</computeroutput>, but
     also lists debugging options which usually are only of use
     to Valgrind's developers.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>--version</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Show the version number of the Valgrind core.  Tools
    can have their own version numbers.  There is a scheme in
    place to ensure that tools only execute when the core version
    is one they are known to work with.  This was done to
    minimise the chances of strange problems arising from
    tool-vs-core version incompatibilities.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>-q --quiet</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Run silently, and only print error messages.  Useful if
    you are running regression tests or have some other automated
    test machinery.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="verbosity">
    <para><computeroutput>-v --verbose</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Be more verbose.  Gives extra information on various
    aspects of your program, such as: the shared objects loaded,
    the suppressions used, the progress of the instrumentation
    and execution engines, and warnings about unusual behaviour.
    Repeating the flag increases the verbosity level.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="trace_children">
    <para><computeroutput>--trace-children=no</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--trace-children=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, Valgrind will trace into child processes.
    This is confusing and usually not what you want, so is
    disabled by default.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="track_fds">
    <para><computeroutput>--track-fds=no</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--track-fds=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, Valgrind will print out a list of open
    file descriptors on exit.  Along with each file descriptor,
    Valgrind prints out a stack backtrace of where the file was
    opened and any details relating to the file descriptor such
    as the file name or socket details.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="time_stamp">
    <para><computeroutput>--time-stamp=no</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--time-stamp=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, Valgrind will precede each message with the
    current time and date.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="log2fd">
    <para><computeroutput>--log-fd=&lt;number&gt;</computeroutput>
    [default: 2, stderr]</para>
    <para>Specifies that Valgrind should send all of its messages
    to the specified file descriptor.  The default, 2, is the
    standard error channel (stderr).  Note that this may
    interfere with the client's own use of stderr.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="log2file_pid">
    <para><computeroutput>--log-file=&lt;filename&gt;</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Specifies that Valgrind should send all of its messages
    to the specified file.  In fact, the file name used is
    created by concatenating the text
    <computeroutput>filename</computeroutput>, ".pid" and the
    process ID, so as to create a file per process.  The
    specified file name may not be the empty string.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="log2file">
    <para><computeroutput>--log-file-exactly=&lt;filename&gt;</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Just like <computeroutput>--log-file</computeroutput>, but
    the ".pid" suffix is not added.  If you trace multiple processes
    with Valgrind when using this option the log file may get all messed
    up.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="log2file_qualifier">
    <para><computeroutput>--log-file-qualifer=&lt;VAR&gt;</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Specifies that Valgrind should send all of its messages
    to the file named by the environment variable
    <computeroutput>$VAR</computeroutput>.  This is useful when running
    MPI programs.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="log2socket">
    <para><computeroutput>--log-socket=&lt;ip-address:port-number&gt;</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Specifies that Valgrind should send all of its messages
    to the specified port at the specified IP address.  The port
    may be omitted, in which case port 1500 is used.  If a
    connection cannot be made to the specified socket, Valgrind
    falls back to writing output to the standard error (stderr).
    This option is intended to be used in conjunction with the
    <computeroutput>valgrind-listener</computeroutput> program.
    For further details, see <xref linkend="manual-core.comment"/>.</para>
   </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
 </sect2>


<sect2 id="manual-core.erropts" xreflabel="Error-related Options">
<title>Error-related options</title>

<para>These options are used by all tools that can report
errors, e.g. Memcheck, but not Cachegrind.</para>

  <itemizedlist>

   <listitem id="xml_output">
    <para><computeroutput>--xml=no</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--xml=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, output will be in XML format.  This is aimed at
    making life easier for tools that consume Valgrind's output as input,
    such as GUI front ends.  Currently this option only works with Memcheck
    and Nulgrind.
    </para>
   </listitem>
    
   <listitem id="xml_user_comment">
    <para><computeroutput>--xml-user-comment=&lt;string&gt;</computeroutput> [default=""]</para>
    <para>Embeds an extra user comment string in the XML output.  Only works
    with <computeroutput>--xml=yes</computeroutput> is specified;  ignored
    otherwise.</para>
   </listitem>
    
   <listitem id="auto_demangle">
    <para><computeroutput>--demangle=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--demangle=yes</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para>Disable/enable automatic demangling (decoding) of C++
    names.  Enabled by default.  When enabled, Valgrind will
    attempt to translate encoded C++ procedure names back to
    something approaching the original.  The demangler handles
    symbols mangled by g++ versions 2.X and 3.X.</para>

    <para>An important fact about demangling is that function
    names mentioned in suppressions files should be in their
    mangled form.  Valgrind does not demangle function names when
    searching for applicable suppressions, because to do
    otherwise would make suppressions file contents dependent on
    the state of Valgrind's demangling machinery, and would also
    be slow and pointless.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="num_callers">
    <para><computeroutput>--num-callers=&lt;number&gt;</computeroutput> [default=4]</para>
    <para>By default, Valgrind shows four levels of function call
    names to help you identify program locations.  You can change
    that number with this option.  This can help in determining
    the program's location in deeply-nested call chains.  Note
    that errors are commoned up using only the top three function
    locations (the place in the current function, and that of its
    two immediate callers).  So this doesn't affect the total
    number of errors reported.</para>

    <para>The maximum value for this is 50.  Note that higher
    settings will make Valgrind run a bit more slowly and take a
    bit more memory, but can be useful when working with programs
    with deeply-nested call chains.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="error_limit">
    <para><computeroutput>--error-limit=yes</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--error-limit=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, Valgrind stops reporting errors after
    30000 in total, or 300 different ones, have been seen.  This
    is to stop the error tracking machinery from becoming a huge
    performance overhead in programs with many errors.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="stack_traces">
    <para><computeroutput>--show-below-main=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--show-below-main=no</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para>By default, stack traces for errors do not show any
    functions that appear beneath
    <computeroutput>main()</computeroutput>; most of the time
    it's uninteresting C library stuff.  If this option is
    enabled, these entries below
    <computeroutput>main()</computeroutput> will be shown.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="supps_files">
    <para><computeroutput>--suppressions=&lt;filename&gt;</computeroutput>
    [default: $PREFIX/lib/valgrind/default.supp]</para>
    <para>Specifies an extra file from which to read descriptions
    of errors to suppress.  You may use as many extra
    suppressions files as you like.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="gen_supps">
    <para><computeroutput>--gen-suppressions=no</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--gen-suppressions=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--gen-suppressions=all</computeroutput></para>

    <para>When set to <computeroutput>yes</computeroutput>, Valgrind
    will pause after every error shown, and print the line:
    <computeroutput>---- Print suppression ?  --- [Return/N/n/Y/y/C/c]
    ----</computeroutput></para>

    <para>The prompt's behaviour is the same as for the 
    <computeroutput>--db-attach</computeroutput> option.</para>

    <para>If you choose to, Valgrind will print out a suppression
    for this error.  You can then cut and paste it into a
    suppression file if you don't want to hear about the error in
    the future.</para>

    <para>When set to <computeroutput>all</computeroutput>, Valgrind
    will print a suppression for every reported error, without
    querying the user.</para>

    <para>This option is particularly useful with C++ programs,
    as it prints out the suppressions with mangled names, as
    required.</para>

    <para>Note that the suppressions printed are as specific as
    possible.  You may want to common up similar ones, eg. by
    adding wildcards to function names.  Also, sometimes two
    different errors are suppressed by the same suppression, in
    which case Valgrind will output the suppression more than
    once, but you only need to have one copy in your suppression
    file (but having more than one won't cause problems).  Also,
    the suppression name is given as <computeroutput>&lt;insert a
    suppression name here&gt;</computeroutput>; the name doesn't
    really matter, it's only used with the
    <computeroutput>-v</computeroutput> option which prints out
    all used suppression records.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="attach_debugger">
    <para><computeroutput>--db-attach=no</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--db-attach=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, Valgrind will pause after every error
    shown, and print the line: <computeroutput>---- Attach to
    debugger ? --- [Return/N/n/Y/y/C/c] ----</computeroutput></para>

    <para>Pressing <literal>Ret</literal>, or 
    <literal>N Ret</literal> or <literal>n Ret</literal>, causes
    Valgrind not to start a debugger for this error.</para>

    <para><literal>Y Ret</literal> or <literal>y Ret</literal>
    causes Valgrind to start a debugger, for the program at this
    point.  When you have finished with the debugger, quit from
    it, and the program will continue.  Trying to continue from
    inside the debugger doesn't work.</para>

    <para><literal>C Ret</literal> or <literal>c Ret</literal>
    causes Valgrind not to start a debugger, and not to ask
    again.</para>

    <formalpara>
     <title>Note:</title>
     <para><computeroutput>--db-attach=yes</computeroutput>
     conflicts with
     <computeroutput>--trace-children=yes</computeroutput>.  You
     can't use them together.  Valgrind refuses to start up in
     this situation.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <para>1 May 2002: this is a historical relic which could be
    easily fixed if it gets in your way.  Mail me and complain if
    this is a problem for you.</para> <para>Nov 2002: if you're
    sending output to a logfile or to a network socket, I guess
    this option doesn't make any sense.  Caveat emptor.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="which_debugger">
    <para><computeroutput>--db-command=&lt;command&gt;</computeroutput>
    [default: gdb -nw %f %p]</para>
    <para>This specifies how Valgrind will invoke the debugger.
    By default it will use whatever GDB is detected at build
    time, which is usually
    <computeroutput>/usr/bin/gdb</computeroutput>.  Using this
    command, you can specify some alternative command to invoke
    the debugger you want to use.</para>

    <para>The command string given can include one or instances
    of the <literal>%p</literal> and <literal>%f</literal>
    expansions. Each instance of <literal>%p</literal> expands to
    the PID of the process to be debugged and each instance of
    <literal>%f</literal> expands to the path to the executable
    for the process to be debugged.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="input_fd">
    <para><computeroutput>--input-fd=&lt;number&gt;</computeroutput>
    [default=0, stdin]</para>
    <para>When using
    <computeroutput>--db-attach=yes</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>--gen-suppressions=yes</computeroutput>,
    Valgrind will stop so as to read keyboard input from you,
    when each error occurs.  By default it reads from the
    standard input (stdin), which is problematic for programs
    which close stdin.  This option allows you to specify an
    alternative file descriptor from which to read input.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="max_frames">
    <para><computeroutput>--max-stackframe=&lt;number&gt;</computeroutput>
                          [default=2000000]
    </para>
    <para>You may need to use this option if your program has large
    stack-allocated arrays.  Valgrind keeps track of your program's
    stack pointer.  If it changes by more than the threshold amount,
    Valgrind assumes your program is switching to a different stack,
    and Memcheck behaves differently than it would for a stack pointer
    change smaller than the threshold.  Usually this heuristic works
    well.  However, if your program allocates large structures on the
    stack, this heuristic will be fooled, and Memcheck will
    subsequently report large numbers of invalid stack accesses.  This
    option allows you to change the threshold to a different value.
    </para>
    <para>
    You should only consider use of this flag if Valgrind's debug output
    directs you to do so.  In that case it will tell you the new
    threshold you should specify.
    </para>
    <para>
    In general, allocating large structures on the stack is a bad
    idea, because (1) you can easily run out of stack space,
    especially on systems with limited memory or which expect to
    support large numbers of threads each with a small stack, and (2)
    because the error checking performed by Memcheck is more effective
    for heap-allocated data than for stack-allocated data.  If you
    have to use this flag, you may wish to consider rewriting your
    code to allocate on the heap rather than on the stack.
   </para>
   </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="manual-core.mallocopts" xreflabel="malloc()-related Options">
<title><computeroutput>malloc()</computeroutput>-related Options</title>

<para>For tools that use their own version of
<computeroutput>malloc()</computeroutput> (e.g. Memcheck and
Addrcheck), the following options apply.</para>

  <itemizedlist>

   <listitem id="alignment">
    <para><computeroutput>--alignment=&lt;number&gt;</computeroutput>
    [default: 8]</para>
    <para>By default Valgrind's
    <computeroutput>malloc</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>realloc</computeroutput>, etc, return 8-byte
    aligned addresses.  This is standard for
    most processors.  Some programs might however assume that
    <computeroutput>malloc</computeroutput> et al return 16- or
    more aligned memory.  The supplied value must be between 4
    and 4096 inclusive, and must be a power of two.</para>
   </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>

 </sect2>


 <sect2 id="manual-core.rareopts" xreflabel="Uncommon Options">
  <title>Uncommon Options</title>

  <para>These options apply to all tools, as they affect certain
  obscure workings of the Valgrind core.  Most people won't need
  to use these.</para>

  <itemizedlist>

   <listitem id="free_glibc">
    <para><computeroutput>--run-libc-freeres=yes</computeroutput>
     [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--run-libc-freeres=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para>The GNU C library
    (<computeroutput>libc.so</computeroutput>), which is used by
    all programs, may allocate memory for its own uses.  Usually
    it doesn't bother to free that memory when the program ends -
    there would be no point, since the Linux kernel reclaims all
    process resources when a process exits anyway, so it would
    just slow things down.</para>

    <para>The glibc authors realised that this behaviour causes
    leak checkers, such as Valgrind, to falsely report leaks in
    glibc, when a leak check is done at exit.  In order to avoid
    this, they provided a routine called
    <computeroutput>__libc_freeres</computeroutput> specifically
    to make glibc release all memory it has allocated.  Memcheck
    and Addrcheck therefore try and run
    <computeroutput>__libc_freeres</computeroutput> at
    exit.</para>

    <para>Unfortunately, in some versions of glibc,
    <computeroutput>__libc_freeres</computeroutput> is
    sufficiently buggy to cause segmentation faults.  This is
    particularly noticeable on Red Hat 7.1.  So this flag is
    provided in order to inhibit the run of
    <computeroutput>__libc_freeres</computeroutput>.  If your
    program seems to run fine on Valgrind, but segfaults at exit,
    you may find that
    <computeroutput>--run-libc-freeres=no</computeroutput> fixes
    that, although at the cost of possibly falsely reporting
    space leaks in
    <computeroutput>libc.so</computeroutput>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="weird_hacks">
    <para><computeroutput>--weird-hacks=hack1,hack2,...</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Pass miscellaneous hints to Valgrind which slightly
    modify the simulated behaviour in nonstandard or dangerous
    ways, possibly to help the simulation of strange features.
    By default no hacks are enabled.  Use with caution!
    Currently known hacks are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para><computeroutput>lax-ioctls</computeroutput></para>
      <para>Be very lax about ioctl handling; the only assumption
      is that the size is correct. Doesn't require the full
      buffer to be initialized when writing.  Without this, using
      some device drivers with a large number of strange ioctl
      commands becomes very tiresome.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem><para><computeroutput>ioctl-mmap</computeroutput></para> 
      <para>Some ioctl requests can mmap new memory into your
      process address space.  If Valgrind doesn't know about these mappings,
      it could put new mappings over them, and/or complain bitterly when
      your program uses them.  This option makes Valgrind scan the address
      space for new mappings after each unknown ioctl has finished.  You may
      also need to run with
      <computeroutput>--pointercheck=no</computeroutput> if the ioctl
      decides to place the mapping out of the client's usual address space.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="pointer_check">
    <para><computeroutput>--pointercheck=yes</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--pointercheck=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para>This option make Valgrind generate a check on every memory
    reference to make sure it is within the client's part of the
    address space.  This prevents stray writes from damaging
    Valgrind itself.  On x86, this uses the CPU's segmentation
    machinery, and has almost no performance cost; there's almost
    never a reason to turn it off.  On the other architectures this 
    option is currently ignored as they don't have a cheap way of achieving
    the same functionality.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="show_emwarns">
    <para><computeroutput>--show-emwarns=no</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--show-emwarns=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, Valgrind will emit warnings about its CPU emulation
    in certain cases.  These are usually not interesting.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem id="smc_support">
    <para><computeroutput>--smc-check=none</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--smc-check=stack</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--smc-check=all</computeroutput></para>
    <para>This option controls Valgrind's detection of self-modifying code.
    Valgrind can do no detection, detect self-modifying code on the stack,
    or detect self-modifying code anywhere.  Note that the default option
    will catch the vast majority of cases, as far as we know.  Running with
    <computeroutput>all</computeroutput> will slow Valgrind down greatly
    (but running with <computeroutput>none</computeroutput> will rarely
    speed things up, since very little code gets put on the stack for most
    programs). </para>
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
</sect2>


<sect2 id="manual-core.debugopts" xreflabel="Debugging Valgrind Options">
<title>Debugging Valgrind Options</title>

<para>There are also some options for debugging Valgrind itself.
You shouldn't need to use them in the normal run of things.  If you
wish to see the list, use the <computeroutput>--help-debug</computeroutput>
option.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="manual-core.defopts" xreflabel="Setting default options">
<title>Setting default Options</title>

<para>Note that Valgrind also reads options from three places:</para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>The file <computeroutput>~/.valgrindrc</computeroutput></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>The environment variable
    <computeroutput>$VALGRIND_OPTS</computeroutput></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>The file <computeroutput>./.valgrindrc</computeroutput></para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

<para>These are processed in the given order, before the
command-line options.  Options processed later override those
processed earlier; for example, options in
<computeroutput>./.valgrindrc</computeroutput> will take
precedence over those in
<computeroutput>~/.valgrindrc</computeroutput>.  The first two
are particularly useful for setting the default tool to
use.</para>

<para>Any tool-specific options put in
<computeroutput>$VALGRIND_OPTS</computeroutput> or the
<computeroutput>.valgrindrc</computeroutput> files should be
prefixed with the tool name and a colon.  For example, if you
want Memcheck to always do leak checking, you can put the
following entry in <literal>~/.valgrindrc</literal>:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
--memcheck:leak-check=yes]]></programlisting>

<para>This will be ignored if any tool other than Memcheck is
run.  Without the <computeroutput>memcheck:</computeroutput>
part, this will cause problems if you select other tools that
don't understand
<computeroutput>--leak-check=yes</computeroutput>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.clientreq" 
       xreflabel="The Client Request mechanism">
<title>The Client Request mechanism</title>

<para>Valgrind has a trapdoor mechanism via which the client
program can pass all manner of requests and queries to Valgrind
and the current tool.  Internally, this is used extensively to
make malloc, free, signals, threads, etc, work, although you
don't see that.</para>

<para>For your convenience, a subset of these so-called client
requests is provided to allow you to tell Valgrind facts about
the behaviour of your program, and conversely to make queries.
In particular, your program can tell Valgrind about changes in
memory range permissions that Valgrind would not otherwise know
about, and so allows clients to get Valgrind to do arbitrary
custom checks.</para>

<para>Clients need to include a header file to make this work.
Which header file depends on which client requests you use.  Some
client requests are handled by the core, and are defined in the
header file <filename>valgrind/valgrind.h</filename>.  Tool-specific
header files are named after the tool, e.g.
<filename>valgrind/memcheck.h</filename>.  All header files can be found
in the <literal>include/valgrind</literal> directory of wherever Valgrind
was installed.</para>

<para>The macros in these header files have the magical property
that they generate code in-line which Valgrind can spot.
However, the code does nothing when not run on Valgrind, so you
are not forced to run your program under Valgrind just because you
use the macros in this file.  Also, you are not required to link your
program with any extra supporting libraries.</para>

<para>The code left in your binary has negligible performance impact.
However, if you really wish to compile out the client requests, you can
compile with <computeroutput>-DNVALGRIND</computeroutput> (analogous to
<computeroutput>-DNDEBUG</computeroutput>'s effect on
<computeroutput>assert()</computeroutput>).
</para>

<para>You are encouraged to copy the <filename>valgrind/*.h</filename> headers
into your project's include directory, so your program doesn't have a
compile-time dependency on Valgrind being installed.  The Valgrind headers,
unlike the rest of the code, is under a BSD-style license so you may include
them without worrying about license incompatibility.</para>

<para>Here is a brief description of the macros available in
<filename>valgrind.h</filename>, which work with more than one
tool (see the tool-specific documentation for explanations of the
tool-specific macros).</para>

 <variablelist>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>RUNNING_ON_VALGRIND</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>returns 1 if running on Valgrind, 0 if running on the
    real CPU.  If you are running Valgrind under itself, it will return the
    number of layers of Valgrind emulation we're running under.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_DISCARD_TRANSLATIONS</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>discard translations of code in the specified address
    range.  Useful if you are debugging a JITter or some other
    dynamic code generation system.  After this call, attempts to
    execute code in the invalidated address range will cause
    Valgrind to make new translations of that code, which is
    probably the semantics you want.  Note that this is
    implemented naively, and involves checking all 200191 entries
    in the translation table to see if any of them overlap the
    specified address range.  So try not to call it often, or
    performance will nosedive.  Note that you can be clever about
    this: you only need to call it when an area which previously
    contained code is overwritten with new code.  You can choose
    to write coode into fresh memory, and just call this
    occasionally to discard large chunks of old code all at
    once.</para>

    <para><command>Warning:</command> minimally tested,
    especially for tools other than Memcheck.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_COUNT_ERRORS</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>returns the number of errors found so far by Valgrind.
    Can be useful in test harness code when combined with the
    <computeroutput>--log-fd=-1</computeroutput> option; this
    runs Valgrind silently, but the client program can detect
    when errors occur.  Only useful for tools that report errors,
    e.g. it's useful for Memcheck, but for Cachegrind it will
    always return zero because Cachegrind doesn't report
    errors.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_MALLOCLIKE_BLOCK</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>If your program manages its own memory instead of using
    the standard <computeroutput>malloc()</computeroutput> /
    <computeroutput>new</computeroutput> /
    <computeroutput>new[]</computeroutput>, tools that track
    information about heap blocks will not do nearly as good a
    job.  For example, Memcheck won't detect nearly as many
    errors, and the error messages won't be as informative.  To
    improve this situation, use this macro just after your custom
    allocator allocates some new memory.  See the comments in
    <filename>valgrind.h</filename> for information on how to use
    it.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_FREELIKE_BLOCK</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>This should be used in conjunction with
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_MALLOCLIKE_BLOCK</computeroutput>.
    Again, see <filename>memcheck/memcheck.h</filename> for
    information on how to use it.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_CREATE_MEMPOOL</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>This is similar to
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_MALLOCLIKE_BLOCK</computeroutput>,
    but is tailored towards code that uses memory pools.  See the
    comments in <filename>valgrind.h</filename> for information
    on how to use it.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  
  <varlistentry>
  <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_DESTROY_MEMPOOL</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>This should be used in conjunction with
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_CREATE_MEMPOOL</computeroutput>
    Again, see the comments in <filename>valgrind.h</filename> for
    information on how to use it.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_ALLOC</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>This should be used in conjunction with
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_CREATE_MEMPOOL</computeroutput>
    Again, see the comments in <filename>valgrind.h</filename> for
    information on how to use it.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
   
  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_FREE</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>This should be used in conjunction with
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_CREATE_MEMPOOL</computeroutput>
    Again, see the comments in <filename>valgrind.h</filename> for
    information on how to use it.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_NON_SIMD_CALL[0123]</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>executes a function of 0, 1, 2 or 3 args in the client
    program on the <emphasis>real</emphasis> CPU, not the virtual
    CPU that Valgrind normally runs code on.  These are used in
    various ways internally to Valgrind.  They might be useful to
    client programs.</para> <formalpara><title>Warning:</title>
    <para>Only use these if you <emphasis>really</emphasis> know
    what you are doing.</para>
    </formalpara>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_PRINTF(format, ...)</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>printf a message to the log file when running under
    Valgrind.  Nothing is output if not running under Valgrind.
    Returns the number of characters output.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_PRINTF_BACKTRACE(format, ...)</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>printf a message to the log file along with a stack
    backtrace when running under Valgrind.  Nothing is output if
    not running under Valgrind.  Returns the number of characters
    output.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_STACK_REGISTER(start, end)</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>Register a new stack.  Informs Valgrind that the memory range
    between start and end is a unique stack.  Returns a stack identifier
    that can be used with other
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_STACK_*</computeroutput> calls.</para>
    <para>Valgrind will use this information to determine if a change to
    the stack pointer is an item pushed onto the stack or a change over
    to a new stack.  Use this if you're using a user-level thread package
    and are noticing spurious errors from Valgrind about uninitialized
    memory reads.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_STACK_DEREGISTER(id)</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>Deregister a previously registered stack.  Informs
    Valgrind that previously registered memory range with stack id
    <computeroutput>id</computeroutput> is no longer a stack.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
   <term><computeroutput>VALGRIND_STACK_CHANGE(id, start, end)</computeroutput>:</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>Change a previously registered stack.  Informs
    Valgrind that the previously registerer stack with stack id
    <computeroutput>id</computeroutput> has changed it's start and end
    values.  Use this if your user-level thread package implements
    stack growth.</para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

 </variablelist>

<para>Note that <filename>valgrind.h</filename> is included by
all the tool-specific header files (such as
<filename>memcheck.h</filename>), so you don't need to include it
in your client if you include a tool-specific header.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="manual-core.pthreads" xreflabel="Support for Threads">
<title>Support for Threads</title>

<para>Valgrind supports programs which use POSIX pthreads.
Getting this to work was technically challenging but it all works
well enough for significant threaded applications to work.</para>

<para>The main thing to point out is that although Valgrind works
with the built-in threads system (eg. NPTL or LinuxThreads), it
serialises execution so that only one thread is running at a time.  This
approach avoids the horrible implementation problems of implementing a
truly multiprocessor version of Valgrind, but it does mean that threaded
apps run only on one CPU, even if you have a multiprocessor
machine.</para>

<para>Valgrind schedules your program's threads in a round-robin fashion,
with all threads having equal priority.  It switches threads
every 50000 basic blocks (on x86, typically around 300000
instructions), which means you'll get a much finer interleaving
of thread executions than when run natively.  This in itself may
cause your program to behave differently if you have some kind of
concurrency, critical race, locking, or similar, bugs.</para>

<!--
<para>It works as follows: threaded apps are (dynamically) linked
against <literal>libpthread.so</literal>.  Usually this is the
one installed with your Linux distribution.  Valgrind, however,
supplies its own <literal>libpthread.so</literal> and
automatically connects your program to it instead.</para>

<para>The fake <literal>libpthread.so</literal> and Valgrind
cooperate to implement a user-space pthreads package.  This
approach avoids the horrible implementation problems of
implementing a truly multiprocessor version of Valgrind, but it
does mean that threaded apps run only on one CPU, even if you
have a multiprocessor machine.</para>

<para>Your program will use the native
<computeroutput>libpthread</computeroutput>, but not all of its facilities
will work.  In particular, process-shared synchronization WILL NOT
WORK.  They rely on special atomic instruction sequences which
Valgrind does not emulate in a way which works between processes.
Unfortunately there's no way for Valgrind to warn when this is happening,
and such calls will mostly work; it's only when there's a race will it fail.
</para>

<para>Valgrind also supports direct use of the
<computeroutput>clone()</computeroutput> system call,
<computeroutput>futex()</computeroutput> and so on.
<computeroutput>clone()</computeroutput> is supported where either
everything is shared (a thread) or nothing is shared (fork-like); partial
sharing will fail.  Again, any use of atomic instruction sequences in shared
memory between processes will not work.
</para>

<para>Valgrind schedules your threads in a round-robin fashion,
with all threads having equal priority.  It switches threads
every 50000 basic blocks (on x86, typically around 300000
instructions), which means you'll get a much finer interleaving
of thread executions than when run natively.  This in itself may
cause your program to behave differently if you have some kind of
concurrency, critical race, locking, or similar, bugs.</para>

<para>As of the Valgrind-1.0 release, the state of pthread
support was as follows:</para>

 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
   <para>Mutexes, condition variables, thread-specific data,
   <computeroutput>pthread_once</computeroutput>, reader-writer
   locks, semaphores, cleanup stacks, cancellation and thread
   detaching currently work.  Various attribute-like calls are
   handled but ignored; you get a warning message.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Currently the following syscalls are thread-safe
   (nonblocking): <literal>write</literal>,
   <literal>read</literal>, <literal>nanosleep</literal>,
   <literal>sleep</literal>, <literal>select</literal>,
   <literal>poll</literal>, <literal>recvmsg</literal> and
   <literal>accept</literal>.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Signals in pthreads are now handled properly(ish):
   <literal>pthread_sigmask</literal>,
   <literal>pthread_kill</literal>, <literal>sigwait</literal>
   and <literal>raise</literal> are now implemented.  Each thread
   has its own signal mask, as POSIX requires.  It's a bit
   kludgey - there's a system-wide pending signal set, rather
   than one for each thread.  But hey.</para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>

<formalpara>
<title>Note:</title> 
<para>As of 18 May 2002, the following threaded programs now work
fine on my RedHat 7.2 box: Opera 6.0Beta2, KNode in KDE 3.0,
Mozilla-0.9.2.1 and Galeon-0.11.3, both as supplied with RedHat
7.2.  Also Mozilla 1.0RC2.  OpenOffice 1.0.  MySQL 3.something
(the current stable release).</para>
</formalpara>
-->

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.signals" xreflabel="Handling of Signals">
<title>Handling of Signals</title>

<para>Valgrind has a fairly complete signal implementation.  It should be
able to cope with any valid use of signals.</para>
 
<para>If you're using signals in clever ways (for example, catching
SIGSEGV, modifying page state and restarting the instruction), you're
probably relying on precise exceptions.  In this case, you will need
to use <computeroutput>--single-step=yes</computeroutput>.</para>

<para>If your program dies as a result of a fatal core-dumping signal,
Valgrind will generate its own core file
(<computeroutput>vgcore.pidNNNNN</computeroutput>) containing your program's
state.  You may use this core file for post-mortem debugging with gdb or
similar.  (Note: it will not generate a core if your core dump size limit is
0.)</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="manual-core.install" xreflabel="Building and Installing">
<title>Building and Installing</title>

<para>We use the standard Unix
<computeroutput>./configure</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>make</computeroutput>, <computeroutput>make
install</computeroutput> mechanism, and we have attempted to
ensure that it works on machines with kernel 2.4 or 2.6 and glibc
2.2.X, 2.3.X, 2.4.X.</para>

<para>There are two options (in addition to the usual
<computeroutput>--prefix=</computeroutput> which affect how Valgrind is built:
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
  <para><computeroutput>--enable-pie</computeroutput></para>
  <para>PIE stands for "position-independent executable".
  PIE allows Valgrind to place itself as high as possible in memory,
  giving your program as much address space as possible.  It also allows
  Valgrind to run under itself.  If PIE is disabled, Valgrind loads at a
  default address which is suitable for most systems.  This is also
  useful for debugging Valgrind itself.  It's not on by default because
  it caused problems for some people.  Note that not all toolchaines
  support PIEs, you need fairly recent version of the compiler, linker,
  etc.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para><computeroutput>--enable-tls</computeroutput></para>
  <para>TLS (Thread Local Storage) is a relatively new mechanism which
  requires compiler, linker and kernel support.  Valgrind automatically test
  if TLS is supported and enable this option.  Sometimes it cannot test for
  TLS, so this option allows you to override the automatic test.</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>The <computeroutput>configure</computeroutput> script tests
the version of the X server currently indicated by the current
<computeroutput>$DISPLAY</computeroutput>.  This is a known bug.
The intention was to detect the version of the current XFree86
client libraries, so that correct suppressions could be selected
for them, but instead the test checks the server version.  This
is just plain wrong.</para>

<para>If you are building a binary package of Valgrind for
distribution, please read <literal>README_PACKAGERS</literal>
<xref linkend="dist.readme-packagers"/>.  It contains some
important information.</para>

<para>Apart from that, there's not much excitement here.  Let us
know if you have build problems.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="manual-core.problems" xreflabel="If You Have Problems">
<title>If You Have Problems</title>

<para>Contact us at <ulink url="http://www.valgrind.org">http://www.valgrind.org</ulink>.</para>

<para>See <xref linkend="manual-core.limits"/> for the known
limitations of Valgrind, and for a list of programs which are
known not to work on it.</para>

<para>The translator/instrumentor has a lot of assertions in it.
They are permanently enabled, and I have no plans to disable
them.  If one of these breaks, please mail us!</para>

<para>If you get an assertion failure on the expression
<computeroutput>blockSane(ch)</computeroutput> in
<computeroutput>VG_(free)()</computeroutput> in
<filename>m_mallocfree.c</filename>, this may have happened because
your program wrote off the end of a malloc'd block, or before its
beginning.  Valgrind hopefully will have emitted a proper message to that
effect before dying in this way.  This is a known problem which
we should fix.</para>

<para>Read the 
<ulink url="http://www.valgrind.org/docs/FAQ/">FAQ</ulink> for
more advice about common problems, crashes, etc.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="manual-core.limits" xreflabel="Limitations">
<title>Limitations</title>

<para>The following list of limitations seems depressingly long.
However, most programs actually work fine.</para>

<para>Valgrind will run x86/Linux ELF dynamically linked
binaries, on a kernel 2.4.X or 2.6.X system, subject to
the following constraints:</para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>On x86 and AMD64, there is no support for 3DNow! instructions.  If
   the translator encounters these, Valgrind will generate a SIGILL when the
   instruction is executed.  The same is true for Intel's SSE3 SIMD
   instructions.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Atomic instruction sequences are not supported, which will affect
   any use of synchronization objects being shared between processes.  They
   will appear to work, but fail sporadically.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>If your program does its own memory management, rather
   than using malloc/new/free/delete, it should still work, but
   Valgrind's error checking won't be so effective.  If you
   describe your program's memory management scheme using "client
   requests" (Section 3.7 of this manual), Memcheck can do
   better.  Nevertheless, using malloc/new and free/delete is
   still the best approach.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Valgrind's signal simulation is not as robust as it
   could be.  Basic POSIX-compliant sigaction and sigprocmask
   functionality is supplied, but it's conceivable that things
   could go badly awry if you do weird things with signals.
   Workaround: don't.  Programs that do non-POSIX signal tricks
   are in any case inherently unportable, so should be avoided if
   possible.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Machine instructions, and system calls, have been
   implemented on demand.  So it's possible, although unlikely,
   that a program will fall over with a message to that effect.
   If this happens, please report ALL the details printed out, so
   we can try and implement the missing feature.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Memory consumption of your program is majorly increased
   whilst running under Valgrind.  This is due to the large
   amount of administrative information maintained behind the
   scenes.  Another cause is that Valgrind dynamically translates
   the original executable.  Translated, instrumented code is
   14-16 times larger than the original (!) so you can easily end
   up with 30+ MB of translations when running (eg) a web
   browser.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Valgrind can handle dynamically-generated code just
   fine.  If you regenerate code over the top of old code
   (ie. at the same memory addresses), if the code is on the stack Valgrind
   will realise the code has changed, and work correctly.  This is necessary
   to handle the trampolines GCC uses to implemented nested functions.
   If you regenerate code somewhere other than the stack, you will need to
   use the <computeroutput>--smc-check=all</computeroutput> flag, and
   Valgrind will run more slowly than normal.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>As of version 3.0.0, Valgrind has the following limitations
   in its implementation of floating point relative to the IEEE754 standard.
   </para>

   <para>Precision: There is no support for 80 bit arithmetic.
   Internally, Valgrind represents all FP numbers in 64 bits, and so
   there may be some differences in results.  Whether or not this is
   critical remains to be seen.  Note, the x86/amd64 fldt/fstpt
   instructions (read/write 80-bit numbers) are correctly simulated,
   using conversions to/from 64 bits, so that in-memory images of
   80-bit numbers look correct if anyone wants to see.</para>

   <para>The impression observed from many FP regression tests is that
   the accuracy differences aren't significant.  Generally speaking, if
   a program relies on 80-bit precision, there may be difficulties
   porting it to non x86/amd64 platforms which only support 64-bit FP
   precision.  Even on x86/amd64, the program may get different results
   depending on whether it is compiled to use SSE2 instructions
   (64-bits only), or x87 instructions (80-bit).  The net effect is to
   make FP programs behave as if they had been run on a machine with
   64-bit IEEE floats, for example PowerPC.  On amd64 FP arithmetic is
   done by default on SSE2, so amd64 looks more like PowerPC than x86
   from an FP perspective, and there are far fewer noticable accuracy
   differences than with x86.</para>

   <para>Rounding: Valgrind does observe the 4 IEEE-mandated rounding
   modes (to nearest, to +infinity, to -infinity, to zero) for the
   following conversions: float to integer, integer to float where
   there is a possibility of loss of precision, and float-to-float
   rounding.  For all other FP operations, only the IEEE default mode
   (round to nearest) is supported.</para>

   <para>Numeric exceptions in FP code: IEEE754 defines five types of
   numeric exception that can happen: invalid operation (sqrt of
   negative number, etc), division by zero, overflow, underflow,
   inexact (loss of precision).</para>

   <para>For each exception, two courses of action are defined by 754:
   either (1) a user-defined exception handler may be called, or (2) a
   default action is defined, which "fixes things up" and allows the
   computation to proceed without throwing an exception.</para>

   <para>Currently Valgrind only supports the default fixup actions.
   Again, feedback on the importance of exception support would be
   appreciated.</para>

   <para>When Valgrind detects that the program is trying to exceed any
   of these limitations (setting exception handlers, rounding mode, or
   precision control), it can print a message giving a traceback of
   where this has happened, and continue execution.  This behaviour
   used to be the default, but the messages are annoying and so showing
   them is now optional.  Use
   <computeroutput>--show-emwarns=yes</computeroutput> to see
   them.</para>

   <para>The above limitations define precisely the IEEE754 'default'
   behaviour: default fixup on all exceptions, round-to-nearest
   operations, and 64-bit precision.</para>
  </listitem>
   
  <listitem>
   <para>As of version 3.0.0, Valgrind has the following limitations
   in its implementation of x86/AMD64 SSE2 FP arithmetic.</para>

   <para>Essentially the same: no exceptions, and limited observance
   of rounding mode.  Also, SSE2 has control bits which make it treat
   denormalised numbers as zero (DAZ) and a related action, flush
   denormals to zero (FTZ).  Both of these cause SSE2 arithmetic to be
   less accurate than IEEE requires.  Valgrind detects, ignores, and
   can warn about, attempts to enable either mode.</para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>


 <para>Programs which are known not to work are:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>emacs starts up but immediately concludes it is out of
   memory and aborts.  Emacs has it's own memory-management
   scheme, but I don't understand why this should interact so
   badly with Valgrind.  Emacs works fine if you build it to use
   the standard malloc/free routines.</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>


 <para>Known platform-specific limitations, as of release 2.4.0:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>(none)</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="manual-core.howworks" xreflabel="How It Works - A Rough Overview">
<title>How It Works -- A Rough Overview</title>

<para>Some gory details, for those with a passion for gory
details.  You don't need to read this section if all you want to
do is use Valgrind.  What follows is an outline of the machinery.
It is out of date, as the JITter has been completey rewritten in
version 3.0, and so it works quite differently.
A more detailed (and even more out of date) description is to be
found <xref linkend="mc-tech-docs"/>.</para>

<sect2 id="manual-core.startb" xreflabel="Getting Started">
<title>Getting started</title>

<para>Valgrind is compiled into two executables:
<computeroutput>valgrind</computeroutput>, and
<computeroutput>stage2</computeroutput>.
<computeroutput>valgrind</computeroutput> is a statically-linked executable
which loads at the normal address (0x8048000).
<computeroutput>stage2</computeroutput> is a normal dynamically-linked
executable; it is either linked to load at a high address (0xb8000000) or is
a Position Independent Executable.</para>

<para><computeroutput>Valgrind</computeroutput> (also known as <computeroutput>stage1</computeroutput>):
<orderedlist>
 <listitem><para>Decides where to load stage2.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Pads the address space with
    <computeroutput>mmap</computeroutput>, leaving holes only where stage2
    should load.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Loads stage2 in the same manner as
    <computeroutput>execve()</computeroutput> would, but
    "manually".</para></listitem> 
 <listitem><para>Jumps to the start of stage2.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist></para>

<para>Once stage2 is loaded, it uses
<computeroutput>dlopen()</computeroutput> to load the tool, unmaps all
traces of stage1, initializes the client's state, and starts the synthetic
CPU.</para>

<para>Each thread runs in its own kernel thread, and loops in
<computeroutput>VG_(schedule)</computeroutput> as it runs.  When the thread
terminates, <computeroutput>VG_(schedule)</computeroutput> returns.  Once
all the threads have terminated, Valgrind as a whole exits.</para>

<para>Each thread also has two stacks.  One is the client's stack, which
is manipulated with the client's instructions.  The other is
Valgrind's internal stack, which is used by all Valgrind's code on
behalf of that thread.  It is important to not get them confused.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="manual-core.engine" 
       xreflabel="The translation/instrumentation engine">
<title>The translation/instrumentation engine</title>

<para>Valgrind does not directly run any of the original
program's code.  Only instrumented translations are run.
Valgrind maintains a translation table, which allows it to find
the translation quickly for any branch target (code address).  If
no translation has yet been made, the translator - a just-in-time
translator - is summoned.  This makes an instrumented
translation, which is added to the collection of translations.
Subsequent jumps to that address will use this
translation.</para>

<para>Valgrind no longer directly supports detection of
self-modifying code.  Such checking is expensive, and in practice
(fortunately) almost no applications need it.  However, to help
people who are debugging dynamic code generation systems, there
is a Client Request (basically a macro you can put in your
program) which directs Valgrind to discard translations in a
given address range.  So Valgrind can still work in this
situation provided the client tells it when code has become
out-of-date and needs to be retranslated.</para>

<para>The JITter translates basic blocks -- blocks of
straight-line-code -- as single entities.  To minimise the
considerable difficulties of dealing with the x86 instruction
set, x86 instructions are first translated to a RISC-like
intermediate code, similar to sparc code, but with an infinite
number of virtual integer registers.  Initially each insn is
translated seperately, and there is no attempt at
instrumentation.</para>

<para>The intermediate code is improved, mostly so as to try and
cache the simulated machine's registers in the real machine's
registers over several simulated instructions.  This is often
very effective.  Also, we try to remove redundant updates of the
simulated machines's condition-code register.</para>

<para>The intermediate code is then instrumented, giving more
intermediate code.  There are a few extra intermediate-code
operations to support instrumentation; it is all refreshingly
simple.  After instrumentation there is a cleanup pass to remove
redundant value checks.</para>

<para>This gives instrumented intermediate code which mentions
arbitrary numbers of virtual registers.  A linear-scan register
allocator is used to assign real registers and possibly generate
spill code.  All of this is still phrased in terms of the
intermediate code.  This machinery is inspired by the work of
Reuben Thomas (Mite).</para>

<para>Then, and only then, is the final x86 code emitted.  The
intermediate code is carefully designed so that x86 code can be
generated from it without need for spare registers or other
inconveniences.</para>

<para>The translations are managed using a traditional LRU-based
caching scheme.  The translation cache has a default size of
about 14MB.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="manual-core.track" 
       xreflabel="Tracking the Status of Memory">
<title>Tracking the Status of Memory</title>

<para>Each byte in the process' address space has nine bits
associated with it: one A bit and eight V bits.  The A and V bits
for each byte are stored using a sparse array, which flexibly and
efficiently covers arbitrary parts of the 32-bit address space
without imposing significant space or performance overheads for
the parts of the address space never visited.  The scheme used,
and speedup hacks, are described in detail at the top of the
source file <filename>coregrind/vg_memory.c</filename>, so you
should read that for the gory details.</para>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="manual-core.syscalls" xreflabel="System calls">
<title>System calls</title>

<para>All system calls are intercepted.  The memory status map is
consulted before and updated after each call.  It's all rather
tiresome.  See <filename>coregrind/vg_syscalls.c</filename> for
details.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="manual-core.syssignals" xreflabel="Signals">
<title>Signals</title>

<para>All signal-related system calls are intercepted.  If the client
program is trying to set a signal handler, Valgrind makes a note of the
handler address and which signal it is for.  Valgrind then arranges for the
same signal to be delivered to its own handler.</para>

<para>When such a signal arrives, Valgrind's own handler catches
it, and notes the fact.  At a convenient safe point in execution,
Valgrind builds a signal delivery frame on the client's stack and
runs its handler.  If the handler longjmp()s, there is nothing
more to be said.  If the handler returns, Valgrind notices this,
zaps the delivery frame, and carries on where it left off before
delivering the signal.</para>

<para>The purpose of this nonsense is that setting signal
handlers essentially amounts to giving callback addresses to the
Linux kernel.  We can't allow this to happen, because if it did,
signal handlers would run on the real CPU, not the simulated one.
This means the checking machinery would not operate during the
handler run, and, worse, memory permissions maps would not be
updated, which could cause spurious error reports once the
handler had returned.</para>

<para>An even worse thing would happen if the signal handler
longjmp'd rather than returned: Valgrind would completely lose
control of the client program.</para>

<para>Upshot: we can't allow the client to install signal
handlers directly.  Instead, Valgrind must catch, on behalf of
the client, any signal the client asks to catch, and must
delivery it to the client on the simulated CPU, not the real one.
This involves considerable gruesome fakery; see
<filename>coregrind/vg_signals.c</filename> for details.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="manual-core.example" xreflabel="An Example Run">
<title>An Example Run</title>

<para>This is the log for a run of a small program using Memcheck
The program is in fact correct, and the reported error is as the
result of a potentially serious code generation bug in GNU g++
(snapshot 20010527).</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
sewardj@phoenix:~/newmat10$
~/Valgrind-6/valgrind -v ./bogon 
==25832== Valgrind 0.10, a memory error detector for x86 RedHat 7.1.
==25832== Copyright (C) 2000-2001, and GNU GPL'd, by Julian Seward.
==25832== Startup, with flags:
==25832== --suppressions=/home/sewardj/Valgrind/redhat71.supp
==25832== reading syms from /lib/ld-linux.so.2
==25832== reading syms from /lib/libc.so.6
==25832== reading syms from /mnt/pima/jrs/Inst/lib/libgcc_s.so.0
==25832== reading syms from /lib/libm.so.6
==25832== reading syms from /mnt/pima/jrs/Inst/lib/libstdc++.so.3
==25832== reading syms from /home/sewardj/Valgrind/valgrind.so
==25832== reading syms from /proc/self/exe
==25832== loaded 5950 symbols, 142333 line number locations
==25832== 
==25832== Invalid read of size 4
==25832==    at 0x8048724: _ZN10BandMatrix6ReSizeEiii (bogon.cpp:45)
==25832==    by 0x80487AF: main (bogon.cpp:66)
==25832==  Address 0xBFFFF74C is not stack'd, malloc'd or free'd
==25832==
==25832== ERROR SUMMARY: 1 errors from 1 contexts (suppressed: 0 from 0)
==25832== malloc/free: in use at exit: 0 bytes in 0 blocks.
==25832== malloc/free: 0 allocs, 0 frees, 0 bytes allocated.
==25832== For a detailed leak analysis, rerun with: --leak-check=yes
==25832==
==25832== exiting, did 1881 basic blocks, 0 misses.
==25832== 223 translations, 3626 bytes in, 56801 bytes out.]]></programlisting>

<para>The GCC folks fixed this about a week before gcc-3.0
shipped.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="manual-core.warnings" xreflabel="Warning Messages">
<title>Warning Messages You Might See</title>

<para>Most of these only appear if you run in verbose mode
(enabled by <computeroutput>-v</computeroutput>):</para>

 <itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
   <para><computeroutput>More than 50 errors detected.
   Subsequent errors will still be recorded, but in less detail
   than before.</computeroutput></para>
   <para>After 50 different errors have been shown, Valgrind
   becomes more conservative about collecting them.  It then
   requires only the program counters in the top two stack frames
   to match when deciding whether or not two errors are really
   the same one.  Prior to this point, the PCs in the top four
   frames are required to match.  This hack has the effect of
   slowing down the appearance of new errors after the first 50.
   The 50 constant can be changed by recompiling Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para><computeroutput>More than 300 errors detected.  I'm not
   reporting any more.  Final error counts may be inaccurate.  Go
   fix your program!</computeroutput></para>
   <para>After 300 different errors have been detected, Valgrind
   ignores any more.  It seems unlikely that collecting even more
   different ones would be of practical help to anybody, and it
   avoids the danger that Valgrind spends more and more of its
   time comparing new errors against an ever-growing collection.
   As above, the 300 number is a compile-time constant.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para><computeroutput>Warning: client switching
   stacks?</computeroutput></para>
   <para>Valgrind spotted such a large change in the stack
   pointer, <literal>%esp</literal>, that it guesses the client
   is switching to a different stack.  At this point it makes a
   kludgey guess where the base of the new stack is, and sets
   memory permissions accordingly.  You may get many bogus error
   messages following this, if Valgrind guesses wrong.  At the
   moment "large change" is defined as a change of more that
   2000000 in the value of the <literal>%esp</literal> (stack
   pointer) register.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para><computeroutput>Warning: client attempted to close
   Valgrind's logfile fd &lt;number&gt;</computeroutput></para>
   <para>Valgrind doesn't allow the client to close the logfile,
   because you'd never see any diagnostic information after that
   point.  If you see this message, you may want to use the
   <computeroutput>--log-fd=&lt;number&gt;</computeroutput> option
   to specify a different logfile file-descriptor number.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para><computeroutput>Warning: noted but unhandled ioctl
   &lt;number&gt;</computeroutput></para>
   <para>Valgrind observed a call to one of the vast family of
   <computeroutput>ioctl</computeroutput> system calls, but did
   not modify its memory status info (because I have not yet got
   round to it).  The call will still have gone through, but you
   may get spurious errors after this as a result of the
   non-update of the memory info.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para><computeroutput>Warning: set address range perms: large
   range &lt;number></computeroutput></para>
   <para>Diagnostic message, mostly for benefit of the valgrind
   developers, to do with memory permissions.</para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>

</sect1>
</chapter>
