<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[ <!ENTITY % vg-entities SYSTEM "vg-entities.xml"> %vg-entities; ]>

<book id="quick-start" xreflabel="Valgrind Quick Start Guide">

  <bookinfo>
    <title>Valgrind Quick Start Guide</title>
  </bookinfo>


<title>Valgrind Quick Start Guide</title>

<para>The Valgrind distribution has multiple tools.  The most popular is the
memory checking tool (called Memcheck) which can detect many common memory
errors such as:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>touching memory you shouldn't (eg. overrunning heap block 
    boundaries);</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem><para>using values before they have been initialized;</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem><para>incorrect freeing of memory, such as double-freeing heap
  blocks;</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem><para>memory leaks.</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>What follows is the minimum information you need to start detecting
memory errors in your program with Memcheck.  Note that this guide applies
to Valgrind version 2.4.0 and later;  some of the information is not quite
right for earlier versions.</para>

<sect1 id="quick-start.prepare" 
       xreflabel="Preparing your program">
<title>Preparing your program</title>
<para>Compile your program with <computeroutput>-g</computeroutput> to include
debugging information so that Memcheck's error messages include exact line
numbers.  Using <computeroutput>-O0</computeroutput> is also a good idea;
with <computeroutput>-O1</computeroutput> line numbers in error messages can
be inaccurate, and with <computeroutput>-O2</computeroutput> Memcheck
occasionally reports undefined error messages incorrectly.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="quick-start.mcrun" 
       xreflabel="Running your program under Memcheck">
<title>Running your program under Memcheck</title>
<para>If you normally run your program like this:

<programlisting>
  myprog arg1 arg2
</programlisting>

Use this command line:

<programlisting>
  valgrind --leak-check=yes myprog arg1 arg2
</programlisting>

Memcheck is the default tool.  The
<computeroutput>--leak-check</computeroutput> option turns on the detailed
memory leak detector.</para>

<para>Your program will run much slower (eg. 20 to 30 times) than normal,
and use a lot more memory.  Memcheck will issue messages about memory errors
and leaks that it detects.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="quick-start.interpret" 
       xreflabel="Interpreting Memcheck's output">
<title>Interpreting Memcheck's output</title>
<para>Here's an example C program with a memory error and a memory leak.

<programlisting>
  #include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

  void f(void)
  {
     int* x = malloc(10 * sizeof(int));
     x[10] = 0;        // problem 1: heap block overrun
  }                    // problem 2: memory leak -- x not freed

  int main(void)
  {
     f();
     return 0;
  }
</programlisting>

Most error messages look like the following, which describes problem 1, the
heap block overrun:

<programlisting>
  ==19182== Invalid write of size 4
  ==19182==    at 0x804838F: f (example.c:6)
  ==19182==    by 0x80483AB: main (example.c:11)
  ==19182==  Address 0x1BA45050 is 0 bytes after a block of size 40 alloc'd
  ==19182==    at 0x1B8FF5CD: malloc (vg_replace_malloc.c:130)
  ==19182==    by 0x8048385: f (example.c:5)
  ==19182==    by 0x80483AB: main (example.c:11)
</programlisting>

Things to notice:

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
 <para>There is a lot of information in each error message;  read it
 carefully.</para> 
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
 <para>The 19182 is the process ID;  it's usually unimportant.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
 <para>The first line ("Invalid write...") tells you what kind of error it
 is.  Here, the program wrote to some memory it should not have due to a
 heap block overrun.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
 <para>Below the first line is a stack trace telling you where the problem
   occurred.  Stack traces can get quite large, and be confusing, especially
   if you are using the C++ STL.  Reading them from the bottom up can help.
   If the stack trace is not big enough, use the
   <computeroutput>--num-callers</computeroutput> option to make it
   bigger.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
 <para>The addresses (eg. 0x804838F) are usually unimportant, but occasionally
   crucial for tracking down weirder bugs.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
 <para>Some error messages have a second component which describes the memory
   address involved.  This one shows that the written memory is just past
   the end of a block allocated with malloc() on line 7 of example.c.</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

It's worth fixing errors in the order they are reported, as later
errors can be caused by earlier errors.</para>

<para>Memory leak messages look like this:

<programlisting>
  ==19182== 40 bytes in 1 blocks are definitely lost in loss record 1 of 1
  ==19182==    at 0x1B8FF5CD: malloc (vg_replace_malloc.c:130)
  ==19182==    by 0x8048385: f (a.c:5)
  ==19182==    by 0x80483AB: main (a.c:11)
</programlisting>

The stack trace tells you where the leaked memory was allocated.
Memcheck cannot tell you why the memory leaked, unfortunately.  (Ignore the
"vg_replace_malloc.c", that's an implementation detail.)</para>

<para>There are several kinds of leaks;  the two most important categories are:

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>"definitely lost":  your program is leaking memory -- fix
 it!</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem><para>"probably lost":  your program is leaking memory, unless
   you're doing funny things with pointers (such as moving them to point to
   the middle of a heap block).</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

If you don't understand an error message, please consult
<xref linkend="mc-manual.errormsgs"/> in the <xref linkend="manual"/> which has
examples of all the error messages Memcheck produces.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="quick-start.caveats" xreflabel="Caveats">
<title>Caveats</title>
<para>Memcheck is not perfect;  it occasionally produces false positives,
and there are mechanisms for suppressing these (see
<xref linkend="manual-core.suppress"/> in the <xref linkend="manual"/>).
However, it is typically right 99% of the time, so you should be wary of
ignoring its error messages.  After all, you wouldn't ignore warning
messages produced by a compiler, right?</para>

<para>Memcheck also cannot detect every memory error your program has.  For
example, it can't detect if you overrun the bounds of an array that is
allocated statically or on the stack.  But it should detect every error that
could crash your program (eg. cause a segmentation fault).</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="quick-start.info" xreflabel="More Information">
<title>More information</title>
<para>Please consult the <xref linkend="FAQ"/> and the
<xref linkend="manual"/>, which have much more information.  Note that the
other tools in the Valgrind distribution can be invoked with the
<computeroutput>--tool</computeroutput> option.</para>
</sect1>

</book>
