<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="lk-manual" xreflabel="Lackey">

<title>Lackey: a very simple profiler</title>
<para>Lackey is a simple Valgrind tool that does some basic
program measurement.  It adds quite a lot of simple
instrumentation to the program's code.  It is primarily intended
to be of use as an example tool.</para>

<para>It measures and reports:</para>

<orderedlist>

 <listitem>
  <para>The number of calls to
  <computeroutput>_dl_runtime_resolve()</computeroutput>, the
  function in glibc's dynamic linker that resolves function
  references to shared objects.</para>
  <para>You can change the name of the function with command line
  option <computeroutput>--fnname=&lt;name&gt;</computeroutput>.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>The number of conditional branches encountered and the
  number and proportion of those taken.</para>
 </listitem>

 <listitem>

  <para>Statistics about the amount of work done during the execution
  of the client program:</para>  

  <orderedlist>

   <listitem>
    <para>The number of basic blocks entered and completed by the
    program.  Note that due to optimisations done by the JIT, this
    is not really an accurate value.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>The number of guest (x86, amd64, ppc, etc.) instructions and IR
    statements executed.  IR is Valgrind's RISC-like intermediate
    representation via which all instrumentation is done.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Ratios between some of these counts.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>When command line option
    <computeroutput>--detailed-counts=yes</computeroutput> is
    specified, a table is printed with counts of loads, stores and ALU
    operations for various types of operands.</para>

    <para>The types are identified by their IR name ("I1" ... "I128",
    "F32", "F64", and "V128").</para>
   </listitem>

  </orderedlist>

 </listitem>

 <listitem>
  <para>The exit code of the client program.</para>
 </listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>Note that Lackey runs quite slowly, especially when
<computeroutput>--detailed-counts=yes</computeroutput> is specified.
It could be made to run a lot faster by doing a slightly more
sophisticated job of the instrumentation, but that would undermine
its role as a simple example tool.  Hence we have chosen not to do
so.</para>

</chapter>
