<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[ <!ENTITY % vg-entities SYSTEM "../../docs/xml/vg-entities.xml"> %vg-entities; ]>


<chapter id="drd-manual" xreflabel="DRD: a thread error detector">
  <title>DRD: a thread error detector</title>

<para>To use this tool, you must specify
<computeroutput>--tool=drd</computeroutput>
on the Valgrind command line.</para>


<sect1 id="drd-manual.overview" xreflabel="Overview">
<title>Background</title>

<para>
DRD is a Valgrind tool for detecting errors in multithreaded C and C++
shared-memory programs. The tool works for any program that uses the
POSIX threading primitives or that uses threading concepts built on
top of the POSIX threading primitives.
</para>

<sect2 id="drd-manual.mt-progr-models" xreflabel="MT-progr-models">
<title>Multithreaded Programming Paradigms</title>

<para>
For many applications multithreading is a necessity. There are two
reasons why the use of threads may be required:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      To model concurrent activities. Managing the state of one
      activity per thread can be a great simplification compared to
      multiplexing the states of multiple activities in a single
      thread. This is why most server and embedded software is
      multithreaded.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      To let computations run on multiple CPU cores
      simultaneously. This is why many High Performance Computing
      (HPC) applications are multithreaded.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Multithreaded programs can use one or more of the following
paradigms. Which paradigm is appropriate a.o. depends on the
application type -- modeling concurrent activities versus HPC.
Some examples of multithreaded programming paradigms are:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Locking. Data that is shared between threads may only be
      accessed after a lock has been obtained on the mutex associated
      with the shared data item.  A.o. the POSIX threads library, the
      Qt library and the Boost.Thread library support this paradigm
      directly.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Message passing. No data is shared between threads, but threads
      exchange data by passing messages to each other. Well known
      implementations of the message passing paradigm are MPI and
      CORBA.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Automatic parallelization. A compiler converts a sequential
      program into a multithreaded program. The original program may
      or may not contain parallelization hints. As an example,
      <computeroutput>gcc</computeroutput> supports the OpenMP
      standard from gcc version 4.3.0 on. OpenMP is a set of compiler
      directives which tell a compiler how to parallelize a C, C++ or
      Fortran program.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Software Transactional Memory (STM). Data is shared between
      threads, and shared data is updated via transactions. After each
      transaction it is verified whether there were conflicting
      transactions. If there were conflicts, the transaction is
      aborted, otherwise it is committed. This is a so-called
      optimistic approach. There is a prototype of the Intel C
      Compiler (<computeroutput>icc</computeroutput>) available that
      supports STM. Research is ongoing about the addition of STM
      support to <computeroutput>gcc</computeroutput>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
DRD supports any combination of multithreaded programming paradigms as
long as the implementation of these paradigms is based on the POSIX
threads primitives. DRD however does not support programs that use
e.g. Linux' futexes directly. Attempts to analyze such programs with
DRD will cause DRD to report many false positives.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.pthreads-model" xreflabel="Pthreads-model">
<title>POSIX Threads Programming Model</title>

<para>
POSIX threads, also known as Pthreads, is the most widely available
threading library on Unix systems.
</para>

<para>
The POSIX threads programming model is based on the following abstractions:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      A shared address space. All threads running within the same
      process share the same address space. All data, whether shared or
      not, is identified by its address.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Regular load and store operations, which allow to read values
      from or to write values to the memory shared by all threads
      running in the same process.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Atomic store and load-modify-store operations. While these are
      not mentioned in the POSIX threads standard, most
      microprocessors support atomic memory operations. And some
      compilers provide direct support for atomic memory operations
      through built-in functions like
      e.g. <computeroutput>__sync_fetch_and_add()</computeroutput>
      which is supported by both <computeroutput>gcc</computeroutput>
      and <computeroutput>icc</computeroutput>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Threads. Each thread represents a concurrent activity.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Synchronization objects and operations on these synchronization
      objects. The following types of synchronization objects are
      defined in the POSIX threads standard: mutexes, condition
      variables, semaphores, reader-writer locks, barriers and
      spinlocks.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Which source code statements generate which memory accesses depends on
the <emphasis>memory model</emphasis> of the programming language
being used. There is not yet a definitive memory model for the C and
C++ languagues. For a draft memory model, see also document <ulink
url="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2007/n2338.html">
WG21/N2338</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
For more information about POSIX threads, see also the Single UNIX
Specification version 3, also known as
<ulink url="http://www.unix.org/version3/ieee_std.html">
IEEE Std 1003.1</ulink>.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.mt-problems" xreflabel="MT-Problems">
<title>Multithreaded Programming Problems</title>

<para>
Depending on which multithreading paradigm is being used in a program,
one or more of the following problems can occur:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Data races. One or more threads access the same memory
      location without sufficient locking.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Lock contention. One thread blocks the progress of one or more other
      threads by holding a lock too long.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Improper use of the POSIX threads API. The most popular POSIX
      threads implementation, NPTL, is optimized for speed. The NPTL
      will not complain on certain errors, e.g. when a mutex is locked
      in one thread and unlocked in another thread.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Deadlock. A deadlock occurs when two or more threads wait for
      each other indefinitely.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      False sharing. If threads that run on different processor cores
      access different variables located in the same cache line
      frequently, this will slow down the involved threads a lot due
      to frequent exchange of cache lines.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Although the likelihood of the occurrence of data races can be reduced
through a disciplined programming style, a tool for automatic
detection of data races is a necessity when developing multithreaded
software. DRD can detect these, as well as lock contention and
improper use of the POSIX threads API.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.data-race-detection" xreflabel="data-race-detection">
<title>Data Race Detection</title>

<para>
Synchronization operations impose an order on interthread memory
accesses. This order is also known as the happens-before relationship.
</para>

<para>
A multithreaded program is data-race free if all interthread memory
accesses are ordered by synchronization operations.
</para>

<para>
A well known way to ensure that a multithreaded program is data-race
free is to ensure that a locking discipline is followed. It is e.g.
possible to associate a mutex with each shared data item, and to hold
a lock on the associated mutex while the shared data is accessed.
</para>

<para>
All programs that follow a locking discipline are data-race free, but
not all data-race free programs follow a locking discipline. There
exist multithreaded programs where access to shared data is arbitrated
via condition variables, semaphores or barriers. As an example, a
certain class of HPC applications consists of a sequence of
computation steps separated in time by barriers, and where these
barriers are the only means of synchronization.
</para>

<para>
There exist two different algorithms for verifying the correctness of
multithreaded programs at runtime. The so-called Eraser algorithm
verifies whether all shared memory accesses follow a consistent
locking strategy. And the happens-before data race detectors verify
directly whether all interthread memory accesses are ordered by
synchronization operations. While the happens-before data race
detection algorithm is more complex to implement, and while it is more
sensitive to OS scheduling, it is a general approach that works for
all classes of multithreaded programs. Furthermore, the happens-before
data race detection algorithm does not report any false positives.
</para>

<para>
DRD is based on the happens-before algorithm.
</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>


<sect1 id="drd-manual.using-drd" xreflabel="Using DRD">
<title>Using DRD</title>

<sect2 id="drd-manual.options" xreflabel="DRD Options">
<title>Command Line Options</title>

<para>The following command-line options are available for controlling the
behavior of the DRD tool itself:</para>

<!-- start of xi:include in the manpage -->
<variablelist id="drd.opts.list">
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--check-stack-var=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Controls whether <constant>DRD</constant> reports data races
        for stack variables. This is disabled by default in order to
        accelerate data race detection. Most programs do not share
        stack variables over threads.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--exclusive-threshold=<n> [default: off]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Print an error message if any mutex or writer lock has been
        held longer than the specified time (in milliseconds). This
        option enables detecting lock contention.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option>
        <![CDATA[--report-signal-unlocked=<yes|no> [default: yes]]]>
      </option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Whether to report calls to
        <function>pthread_cond_signal()</function> and
        <function>pthread_cond_broadcast()</function> where the mutex
        associated with the signal through
        <function>pthread_cond_wait()</function> or
        <function>pthread_cond_timed_wait()</function>is not locked at
        the time the signal is sent.  Sending a signal without holding
        a lock on the associated mutex is a common programming error
        which can cause subtle race conditions and unpredictable
        behavior. There exist some uncommon synchronization patterns
        however where it is safe to send a signal without holding a
        lock on the associated mutex.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--segment-merging=<yes|no> [default: yes]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Controls segment merging. Segment merging is an algorithm to
        limit memory usage of the data race detection
        algorithm. Disabling segment merging may improve the accuracy
        of the so-called 'other segments' displayed in race reports
        but can also trigger an out of memory error.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--shared-threshold=<n> [default: off]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Print an error message if a reader lock has been held longer
        than the specified time (in milliseconds). This option enables
        detection of lock contention.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--show-confl-seg=<yes|no> [default: yes]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
         Show conflicting segments in race reports. Since this
         information can help to find the cause of a data race, this
         option is enabled by default. Disabling this option makes the
         output of DRD more compact.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--show-stack-usage=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Print stack usage at thread exit time. When a program creates
        a large number of threads it becomes important to limit the
        amount of virtual memory allocated for thread stacks. This
        option makes it possible to observe how much stack memory has
        been used by each thread of the the client program. Note: the
        DRD tool allocates some temporary data on the client thread
        stack itself. The space necessary for this temporary data must
        be allocated by the client program, but is not included in the
        reported stack usage.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--var-info=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Display the names of global, static and stack variables when a
        data race is reported. While this information can be very
        helpful, it is not loaded into memory by default. This is
        because for big programs reading in all debug information at
        once may cause an out of memory error.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<!-- end of xi:include in the manpage -->

<!-- start of xi:include in the manpage -->
<para>
The following options are available for monitoring the behavior of the
client program:
</para>

<variablelist id="drd.debugopts.list">
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-addr=<address> [default: none]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trace all load and store activity for the specified
        address. This option may be specified more than once.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-barrier=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trace all barrier activity.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-cond=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trace all condition variable activity.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-fork-join=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trace all thread creation and all thread termination events.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-mutex=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trace all mutex activity.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-rwlock=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
         Trace all reader-writer lock activity.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--trace-semaphore=<yes|no> [default: no]]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Trace all semaphore activity.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<!-- end of xi:include in the manpage -->

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.data-races" xreflabel="Data Races">
<title>Detected Errors: Data Races</title>

<para>
DRD prints a message every time it detects a data race. Please keep
the following in mind when interpreting DRD's output:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Every thread is assigned two <emphasis>thread ID's</emphasis>:
      one thread ID is assigned by the Valgrind core and one thread ID
      is assigned by DRD. Both thread ID's start at one. Valgrind
      thread ID's are reused when one thread finishes and another
      thread is created. DRD does not reuse thread ID's. Thread ID's
      are displayed e.g. as follows: 2/3, where the first number is
      Valgrind's thread ID and the second number is the thread ID
      assigned by DRD.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The term <emphasis>segment</emphasis> refers to a consecutive
      sequence of load, store and synchronization operations, all
      issued by the same thread. A segment always starts and ends at a
      synchronization operation. Data race analysis is performed
      between segments instead of between individual load and store
      operations because of performance reasons.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      There are always at least two memory accesses involved in a data
      race. Memory accesses involved in a data race are called
      <emphasis>conflicting memory accesses</emphasis>. DRD prints a
      report for each memory access that conflicts with a past memory
      access.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Below you can find an example of a message printed by DRD when it
detects a data race:
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ valgrind --tool=drd --var-info=yes drd/tests/rwlock_race
...
==9466== Thread 3:
==9466== Conflicting load by thread 3/3 at 0x006020b8 size 4
==9466==    at 0x400B6C: thread_func (rwlock_race.c:29)
==9466==    by 0x4C291DF: vg_thread_wrapper (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:186)
==9466==    by 0x4E3403F: start_thread (in /lib64/libpthread-2.8.so)
==9466==    by 0x53250CC: clone (in /lib64/libc-2.8.so)
==9466== Location 0x6020b8 is 0 bytes inside local var "s_racy"
==9466== declared at rwlock_race.c:18, in frame #0 of thread 3
==9466== Other segment start (thread 2/2)
==9466==    at 0x4C2847D: pthread_rwlock_rdlock* (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:813)
==9466==    by 0x400B6B: thread_func (rwlock_race.c:28)
==9466==    by 0x4C291DF: vg_thread_wrapper (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:186)
==9466==    by 0x4E3403F: start_thread (in /lib64/libpthread-2.8.so)
==9466==    by 0x53250CC: clone (in /lib64/libc-2.8.so)
==9466== Other segment end (thread 2/2)
==9466==    at 0x4C28B54: pthread_rwlock_unlock* (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:912)
==9466==    by 0x400B84: thread_func (rwlock_race.c:30)
==9466==    by 0x4C291DF: vg_thread_wrapper (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:186)
==9466==    by 0x4E3403F: start_thread (in /lib64/libpthread-2.8.so)
==9466==    by 0x53250CC: clone (in /lib64/libc-2.8.so)
...
]]></programlisting>

<para>
The above report has the following meaning:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The number in the column on the left is the process ID of the
      process being analyzed by DRD.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The first line ("Thread 3") tells you Valgrind's thread ID for
      the thread in which context the data race was detected.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      The next line tells which kind of operation was performed (load
      or store) and by which thread. Both Valgrind's and DRD's thread
      ID's are displayed. On the same line the start address and the
      number of bytes involved in the conflicting access are also
      displayed.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Next, the call stack of the conflicting access is displayed. If
      your program has been compiled with debug information (-g), this
      call stack will include file names and line numbers. The two
      bottommost frames in this call stack (<function>clone</function>
      and <function>start_thread</function>) show how the NPTL starts
      a thread. The third frame
      (<function>vg_thread_wrapper</function>) is added by DRD. The
      fourth frame (<function>thread_func</function>) is the first
      interesting line because it shows the thread entry point, that
      is the function that has been passed as the third argument to
      <function>pthread_create()</function>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Next, the allocation context for the conflicting address is
      displayed. For dynamically allocated data the allocation call
      stack is shown. For static variables and stack variables the
      allocation context is only shown when the option
      <computeroutput>--var-info=yes</computeroutput> has been
      specified. Otherwise DRD will print <computeroutput>Allocation
      context: unknown</computeroutput>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      A conflicting access involves at least two memory accesses. For
      one of these accesses an exact call stack is displayed, and for
      the other accesses an approximate call stack is displayed,
      namely the start and the end of the segments of the other
      accesses. This information can be interpreted as follows:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Start at the bottom of both call stacks, and count the
            number stack frames with identical function name, file
            name and line number. In the above example the three
            bottommost frames are identical
            (<function>clone</function>,
            <function>start_thread</function> and
            <function>vg_thread_wrapper</function>).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The next higher stack frame in both call stacks now tells
            you between in which source code region the other memory
            access happened. The above output tells that the other
            memory access involved in the data race happened between
            source code lines 28 and 30 in file
            <computeroutput>rwlock_race.c</computeroutput>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.lock-contention" xreflabel="Lock Contention">
<title>Detected Errors: Lock Contention</title>

<para>
Threads must be able to make progress without being blocked for too
long by other threads. Sometimes a thread has to wait until a mutex or
reader-writer lock is unlocked by another thread. This is called
<emphasis>lock contention</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>
Lock contention causes delays. Such delays should be as short as
possible. The two command line options
<literal>--exclusive-threshold=&lt;n&gt;</literal> and
<literal>--shared-threshold=&lt;n&gt;</literal> make it possible to
detect excessive lock contention by making DRD report any lock that
has been held longer than the specified threshold. An example:
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ valgrind --tool=drd --exclusive-threshold=10 drd/tests/hold_lock -i 500
...
==10668== Acquired at:
==10668==    at 0x4C267C8: pthread_mutex_lock (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:395)
==10668==    by 0x400D92: main (hold_lock.c:51)
==10668== Lock on mutex 0x7fefffd50 was held during 503 ms (threshold: 10 ms).
==10668==    at 0x4C26ADA: pthread_mutex_unlock (drd_pthread_intercepts.c:441)
==10668==    by 0x400DB5: main (hold_lock.c:55)
...
]]></programlisting>

<para>
The <literal>hold_lock</literal> test program holds a lock as long as
specified by the <literal>-i</literal> (interval) argument. The DRD
output reports that the lock acquired at line 51 in source file
<literal>hold_lock.c</literal> and released at line 55 was held during
503 ms, while a threshold of 10 ms was specified to DRD.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.api-checks" xreflabel="API Checks">
<title>Detected Errors: Misuse of the POSIX threads API</title>

<para>
  DRD is able to detect and report the following misuses of the POSIX
  threads API:
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Passing the address of one type of synchronization object
        (e.g. a mutex) to a POSIX API call that expects a pointer to
        another type of synchronization object (e.g. a condition
        variable).
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Attempts to unlock a mutex that has not been locked.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Attempts to unlock a mutex that was locked by another thread.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Attempts to lock a mutex of type
        <literal>PTHREAD_MUTEX_NORMAL</literal> or a spinlock
        recursively.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Destruction or deallocation of a locked mutex.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Sending a signal to a condition variable while no lock is held
        on the mutex associated with the signal.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Calling <function>pthread_cond_wait()</function> on a mutex
        that is not locked, that is locked by another thread or that
        has been locked recursively.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Associating two different mutexes with a condition variable
        through <function>pthread_cond_wait()</function>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Destruction or deallocation of a condition variable that is
        being waited upon.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Destruction or deallocation of a locked reader-writer lock.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Attempts to unlock a reader-writer lock that was not locked by
        the calling thread.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Attempts to recursively lock a reader-writer lock exclusively.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Reinitialization of a mutex, condition variable, reader-writer
        lock, semaphore or barrier.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Destruction or deallocation of a semaphore or barrier that is
        being waited upon.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Exiting a thread without first unlocking the spinlocks,
        mutexes or reader-writer locks that were locked by that
        thread.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.clientreqs" xreflabel="Client requests">
<title>Client Requests</title>

<para>
Just as for other Valgrind tools it is possible to let a client
program interact with the DRD tool.
</para>

<para>
The interface between client programs and the DRD tool is defined in
the header file <literal>&lt;valgrind/drd.h&gt;</literal>. The
available client requests are:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_GET_VALGRIND_THREAD_ID</varname>.
      Query the thread ID that was assigned by the Valgrind core to
      the thread executing this client request. Valgrind's thread ID's
      start at one and are recycled in case a thread stops.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_GET_DRD_THREAD_ID</varname>.
      Query the thread ID that was assigned by DRD to
      the thread executing this client request. DRD's thread ID's
      start at one and are never recycled.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_START_SUPPRESSION</varname>. Some
      applications contain intentional races. There exist
      e.g. applications where the same value is assigned to a shared
      variable from two different threads. It may be more convenient
      to suppress such races than to solve these. This client request
      allows to suppress such races. See also the macro
      <literal>DRD_IGNORE_VAR(x)</literal> defined in
      <literal>&lt;valgrind/drd.h&gt;</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_FINISH_SUPPRESSION</varname>. Tell DRD
      to no longer ignore data races in the address range that was
      suppressed via
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_START_SUPPRESSION</varname>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_START_TRACE_ADDR</varname>. Trace all
      load and store activity on the specified address range. When DRD
      reports a data race on a specified variable, and it's not
      immediately clear which source code statements triggered the
      conflicting accesses, it can be helpful to trace all activity on
      the offending memory location. See also the macro
      <literal>DRD_TRACE_VAR(x)</literal> defined in
      <literal>&lt;valgrind/drd.h&gt;</literal>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <varname>VG_USERREQ__DRD_STOP_TRACE_ADDR</varname>. Do no longer
      trace load and store activity for the specified address range.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Note: if you compiled Valgrind yourself, the header file
<literal>&lt;valgrind/drd.h&gt;</literal> will have been installed in
the directory <literal>/usr/include</literal> by the command
<literal>make install</literal>. If you obtained Valgrind by
installing it as a package however, you will probably have to install
another package with a name like <literal>valgrind-devel</literal>
before Valgrind's header files are present.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.gnome" xreflabel="GNOME">
<title>Debugging GNOME Programs</title>

<para>
GNOME applications use the threading primitives provided by the
<computeroutput>glib</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>gthread</computeroutput> libraries. These libraries
are built on top of POSIX threads, and hence are directly supported by
DRD. Please keep in mind that you have to call
<function>g_thread_init()</function> before creating any threads, or
DRD will report several data races on glib functions. See also the
<ulink
url="http://library.gnome.org/devel/glib/stable/glib-Threads.html">GLib
Reference Manual</ulink> for more information about
<function>g_thread_init()</function>.
</para>

<para>
One of the many facilities provided by the <literal>glib</literal>
library is a block allocator, called <literal>g_slice</literal>. You
have to disable this block allocator when using DRD by adding the
following to the shell environment variables:
<literal>G_SLICE=always-malloc</literal>. See also the <ulink
url="http://library.gnome.org/devel/glib/stable/glib-Memory-Slices.html">GLib
Reference Manual</ulink> for more information.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.qt" xreflabel="Qt">
<title>Debugging Qt Programs</title>

<para>
The Qt library is the GUI library used by the KDE project.  Currently
there are two versions of the Qt library in use: Qt3 by KDE 3 and Qt4
by KDE 4. If possible, use Qt4 instead of Qt3. Qt3 is no longer
supported, and there are known problems with multithreading support in
Qt3. As an example, using QString objects in more than one thread will
trigger race reports (this has been confirmed by Trolltech -- see also
Trolltech task <ulink
url="http://trolltech.com/developer/task-tracker/index_html">#206152</ulink>).
</para>

<para>
Qt4 applications are supported by DRD, but only if the
<literal>libqt4-debuginfo</literal> package has been installed. Some
of the synchronization and threading primitives in Qt4 bypass the
POSIX threads library, and DRD can only intercept these if symbol
information for the Qt4 library is available. DRD won't tell you if it
has not been able to load the Qt4 debug information, but a huge number
of data races will be reported on data protected via
<literal>QMutex</literal> objects.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.boost.thread" xreflabel="Boost.Thread">
<title>Debugging Boost.Thread Programs</title>

<para>
The Boost.Thread library is the threading library included with the
cross-platform Boost Libraries. This threading library is an early
implementation of the upcoming C++0x threading library.
</para>

<para>
Applications that use the Boost.Thread library should run fine under DRD.
</para>

<para>
More information about Boost.Thread can be found here:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Anthony Williams, <ulink
      url="http://www.boost.org/doc/libs/1_37_0/doc/html/thread.html">Boost.Thread</ulink>
      Library Documentation, Boost website, 2007.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Anthony Williams, <ulink
      url="http://www.ddj.com/cpp/211600441">What's New in Boost
      Threads?</ulink>, Recent changes to the Boost Thread library,
      Dr. Dobbs Magazine, October 2008.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.openmp" xreflabel="OpenMP">
<title>Debugging OpenMP Programs</title>

<para>
OpenMP stands for <emphasis>Open Multi-Processing</emphasis>. The
OpenMP standard consists of a set of compiler directives for C, C++
and Fortran programs that allows a compiler to transform a sequential
program into a parallel program. OpenMP is well suited for HPC
applications and allows to work at a higher level compared to direct
use of the POSIX threads API. While OpenMP ensures that the POSIX API
is used correctly, OpenMP programs can still contain data races. So it
makes sense to verify OpenMP programs with a thread checking tool.
</para>

<para>
DRD supports OpenMP shared-memory programs generated by gcc. The gcc
compiler supports OpenMP since version 4.2.0.  Gcc's runtime support
for OpenMP programs is provided by a library called
<literal>libgomp</literal>. The synchronization primites implemented
in this library use Linux' futex system call directly, unless the
library has been configured with the
<literal>--disable-linux-futex</literal> flag. DRD only supports
libgomp libraries that have been configured with this flag and in
which symbol information is present. For most Linux distributions this
means that you will have to recompile gcc. See also the script
<literal>drd/scripts/download-and-build-gcc</literal> in the
Valgrind source tree for an example of how to compile gcc. You will
also have to make sure that the newly compiled
<literal>libgomp.so</literal> library is loaded when OpenMP programs
are started. This is possible by adding a line similar to the
following to your shell startup script:
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=~/gcc-4.3.2/lib64:~/gcc-4.3.2/lib:
]]></programlisting>

<para>
As an example, the test OpenMP test program
<literal>drd/tests/omp_matinv</literal> triggers a data race
when the option -r has been specified on the command line. The data
race is triggered by the following code:
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
#pragma omp parallel for private(j)
for (j = 0; j < rows; j++)
{
  if (i != j)
  {
    const elem_t factor = a[j * cols + i];
    for (k = 0; k < cols; k++)
    {
      a[j * cols + k] -= a[i * cols + k] * factor;
    }
  }
}
]]></programlisting>

<para>
The above code is racy because the variable <literal>k</literal> has
not been declared private. DRD will print the following error message
for the above code:
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ valgrind --check-stack-var=yes --var-info=yes --tool=drd drd/tests/omp_matinv 3 -t 2 -r
...
Conflicting store by thread 1/1 at 0x7fefffbc4 size 4
   at 0x4014A0: gj.omp_fn.0 (omp_matinv.c:203)
   by 0x401211: gj (omp_matinv.c:159)
   by 0x40166A: invert_matrix (omp_matinv.c:238)
   by 0x4019B4: main (omp_matinv.c:316)
Allocation context: unknown.
...
]]></programlisting>
<para>
In the above output the function name <function>gj.omp_fn.0</function>
has been generated by gcc from the function name
<function>gj</function>. Unfortunately the variable name
<literal>k</literal> is not shown as the allocation context -- it is
not clear to me whether this is caused by Valgrind or whether this is
caused by gcc. The most usable information in the above output is the
source file name and the line number where the data race has been detected
(<literal>omp_matinv.c:203</literal>).
</para>

<para>
Note: DRD reports errors on the <literal>libgomp</literal> library
included with gcc 4.2.0 up to and including 4.3.2. This might indicate
a race condition in the POSIX version of <literal>libgomp</literal>.
</para>

<para>
For more information about OpenMP, see also 
<ulink url="http://openmp.org/">openmp.org</ulink>.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.cust-mem-alloc" xreflabel="Custom Memory Allocators">
<title>DRD and Custom Memory Allocators</title>

<para>
DRD tracks all memory allocation events that happen via either the
standard memory allocation and deallocation functions
(<function>malloc</function>, <function>free</function>,
<function>new</function> and <function>delete</function>) or via entry
and exit of stack frames. DRD uses memory allocation and deallocation
information for two purposes:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      To know where the scope ends of POSIX objects that have not been
      destroyed explicitly. It is e.g. not required by the POSIX
      threads standard to call
      <function>pthread_mutex_destroy()</function> before freeing the
      memory in which a mutex object resides.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      To know where the scope of variables ends. If e.g. heap memory
      has been used by one thread, that thread frees that memory, and
      another thread allocates and starts using that memory, no data
      races must be reported for that memory.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
It is essential for correct operation of DRD that the tool knows about
memory allocation and deallocation events. DRD does not yet support
custom memory allocators, so you will have to make sure that any
program which runs under DRD uses the standard memory allocation
functions. As an example, the GNU libstdc++ library can be configured
to use standard memory allocation functions instead of memory pools by
setting the environment variable
<literal>GLIBCXX_FORCE_NEW</literal>. For more information, see also
the <ulink
url="http://gcc.gnu.org/onlinedocs/libstdc++/manual/bk01pt04ch11.html">libstdc++
manual</ulink>.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.drd-versus-memcheck" xreflabel="DRD Versus Memcheck">
<title>DRD Versus Memcheck</title>

<para>
It is essential for correct operation of DRD that there are no memory
errors such as dangling pointers in the client program. Which means that
it is a good idea to make sure that your program is memcheck-clean
before you analyze it with DRD. It is possible however that some of
the memcheck reports are caused by data races. In this case it makes
sense to run DRD before memcheck.
</para>

<para>
So which tool should be run first ? In case both DRD and memcheck
complain about a program, a possible approach is to run both tools
alternatingly and to fix as many errors as possible after each run of
each tool until none of the two tools prints any more error messages.
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.resource-requirements" xreflabel="Resource Requirements">
<title>Resource Requirements</title>

<para>
The requirements of DRD with regard to heap and stack memory and the
effect on the execution time of client programs are as follows:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      When running a program under DRD with default DRD options,
      between 1.1 and 3.6 times more memory will be needed compared to
      a native run of the client program. More memory will be needed
      if loading debug information has been enabled
      (<literal>--var-info=yes</literal>).
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      DRD allocates some of its temporary data structures on the stack
      of the client program threads. This amount of data is limited to
      1 - 2 KB. Make sure that thread stacks are sufficiently large.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Most applications will run between 20 and 50 times slower under
      DRD than a native single-threaded run. Applications such as
      Firefox which perform very much mutex lock / unlock operations
      however will run too slow to be usable under DRD. This issue
      will be addressed in a future DRD version.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="drd-manual.effective-use" xreflabel="Effective Use">
<title>Hints and Tips for Effective Use of DRD</title>

<para>
The following information may be helpful when using DRD:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Make sure that debug information is present in the executable
      being analysed, such that DRD can print function name and line
      number information in stack traces. Most compilers can be told
      to include debug information via compiler option
      <option>-g</option>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Compile with flag <option>-O1</option> instead of
      <option>-O0</option>. This will reduce the amount of generated
      code, may reduce the amount of debug info and will speed up
      DRD's processing of the client program. For more information,
      see also <xref linkend="manual-core.started"/>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      If DRD reports any errors on libraries that are part of your
      Linux distribution like e.g. <literal>libc.so</literal> or
      <literal>libstdc++.so</literal>, installing the debug packages
      for these libraries will make the output of DRD a lot more
      detailed.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      When using C++, do not send output from more than one thread to
      <literal>std::cout</literal>. Doing so would not only
      generate multiple data race reports, it could also result in
      output from several threads getting mixed up.  Either use
      <function>printf()</function> or do the following:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Derive a class from <literal>std::ostreambuf</literal>
          and let that class send output line by line to
          <literal>stdout</literal>. This will avoid that individual
          lines of text produced by different threads get mixed
          up.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create one instance of <literal>std::ostream</literal>
          for each thread. This makes stream formatting settings
          thread-local. Pass a per-thread instance of the class
          derived from <literal>std::ostreambuf</literal> to the
          constructor of each instance. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Let each thread send its output to its own instance of
          <literal>std::ostream</literal> instead of
          <literal>std::cout</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>


<sect1 id="drd-manual.Pthreads" xreflabel="Pthreads">
<title>Using the POSIX Threads API Effectively</title>

<sect2 id="drd-manual.mutex-types" xreflabel="mutex-types">
<title>Mutex types</title>

<para>
The Single UNIX Specification version two defines the following four
mutex types (see also the documentation of <ulink
url="http://www.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/007908799/xsh/pthread_mutexattr_settype.html"><function>pthread_mutexattr_settype()</function></ulink>):
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>normal</emphasis>, which means that no error checking
      is performed, and that the mutex is non-recursive.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>error checking</emphasis>, which means that the mutex
      is non-recursive and that error checking is performed.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>recursive</emphasis>, which means that a mutex may be
      locked recursively.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>default</emphasis>, which means that error checking
      behavior is undefined, and that the behavior for recursive
      locking is also undefined. Or: portable code must neither
      trigger error conditions through the Pthreads API nor attempt to
      lock a mutex of default type recursively.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
In complex applications it is not always clear from beforehand which
mutex will be locked recursively and which mutex will not be locked
recursively. Attempts lock a non-recursive mutex recursively will
result in race conditions that are very hard to find without a thread
checking tool. So either use the error checking mutex type and
consistently check the return value of Pthread API mutex calls, or use
the recursive mutex type.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="drd-manual.condvar" xreflabel="condition-variables">
<title>Condition variables</title>

<para>
A condition variable allows one thread to wake up one or more other
threads. Condition variables are often used to notify one or more
threads about state changes of shared data. Unfortunately it is very
easy to introduce race conditions by using condition variables as the
only means of state information propagation. A better approach is to
let threads poll for changes of a state variable that is protected by
a mutex, and to use condition variables only as a thread wakeup
mechanism. See also the source file
<computeroutput>drd/tests/monitor_example.cpp</computeroutput> for an
example of how to implement this concept in C++. The monitor concept
used in this example is a well known and very useful concept -- see
also Wikipedia for more information about the <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monitor_(synchronization)">monitor</ulink>
concept.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="drd-manual.pctw" xreflabel="pthread_cond_timedwait">
<title>pthread_cond_timedwait() and timeouts</title>

<para>
Historically the function
<function>pthread_cond_timedwait()</function> only allowed the
specification of an absolute timeout, that is a timeout independent of
the time when this function was called. However, almost every call to
this function expresses a relative timeout. This typically happens by
passing the sum of
<computeroutput>clock_gettime(CLOCK_REALTIME)</computeroutput> and a
relative timeout as the third argument. This approach is incorrect
since forward or backward clock adjustments by e.g. ntpd will affect
the timeout. A more reliable approach is as follows:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      When initializing a condition variable through
      pthread_cond_init(), specify that the timeout of
      pthread_cond_timedwait() will use the clock
      <literal>CLOCK_MONOTONIC</literal> instead of
      <literal>CLOCK_REALTIME</literal>. You can do this via
      <computeroutput>pthread_condattr_setclock(...,
      CLOCK_MONOTONIC)</computeroutput>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      When calling <function>pthread_cond_timedwait()</function>, pass
      the sum of
      <computeroutput>clock_gettime(CLOCK_MONOTONIC)</computeroutput>
      and a relative timeout as the third argument.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
See also
<computeroutput>drd/tests/monitor_example.cpp</computeroutput> for an
example.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="drd-manual.naming-threads" xreflabel="naming threads">
<title>Assigning names to threads</title>

<para>
Many applications log information about changes in internal or
external state to a file. When analyzing log files of a multithreaded
application it can be very convenient to know which thread logged
which information. One possible approach is to identify threads in
logging output by including the result of
<function>pthread_self()</function> in every log line. However, this approach
has two disadvantages: there is no direct relationship between these
values and the source code and these values can be different in each
run. A better approach is to assign a brief name to each thread and to
include the assigned thread name in each log line. One possible
approach for managing thread names is as follows:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Allocate a key for the pointer to the thread name through
      <function>pthread_key_create()</function>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Just after thread creation, set the thread name through
      <function>pthread_setspecific()</function>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      In the code that generates the logging information, query the thread
      name by calling <function>pthread_getspecific()</function>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="drd-manual.limitations" xreflabel="Limitations">
<title>Limitations</title>

<para>DRD currently has the following limitations:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      DRD has only been tested on the Linux operating system, and not
      on any of the other operating systems supported by
      Valgrind.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Of the two POSIX threads implementations for Linux, only the
      NPTL (Native POSIX Thread Library) is supported. The older
      LinuxThreads library is not supported.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      DRD, just like memcheck, will refuse to start on Linux
      distributions where all symbol information has been removed from
      ld.so. This is a.o. the case for the PPC editions of openSUSE
      and Gentoo. You will have to install the glibc debuginfo package
      on these platforms before you can use DRD. See also openSUSE bug
      <ulink url="http://bugzilla.novell.com/show_bug.cgi?id=396197">
      396197</ulink> and Gentoo bug <ulink
      url="http://bugs.gentoo.org/214065">214065</ulink>.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      When DRD prints a report about a data race detected on a stack
      variable in a parallel section of an OpenMP program, the report
      will contain no information about the context of the data race
      location (<computeroutput>Allocation context:
      unknown</computeroutput>). It's not yet clear whether this
      behavior is caused by Valgrind or by gcc.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      When address tracing is enabled, no information on atomic stores
      will be displayed. This functionality is easy to add
      however. Please contact the Valgrind authors if you would like
      to see this functionality enabled.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      If you compile the DRD source code yourself, you need gcc 3.0 or
      later. Gcc 2.95 is not supported.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="drd-manual.feedback" xreflabel="Feedback">
<title>Feedback</title>

<para>
If you have any comments, suggestions, feedback or bug reports about
DRD, feel free to either post a message on the Valgrind users mailing
list or to file a bug report. See also <ulink
url="&vg-url;">&vg-url;</ulink> for more information.
</para>

</sect1>


</chapter>
