<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">


<chapter id="mc-manual" xreflabel="Memcheck: a heavyweight memory checker">
<title>Memcheck: a heavyweight memory checker</title>

<para>To use this tool, you may specify <option>--tool=memcheck</option>
on the Valgrind command line.  You don't have to, though, since Memcheck
is the default tool.</para>


<sect1 id="mc-manual.bugs" 
       xreflabel="Kinds of bugs that Memcheck can find">
<title>Kinds of bugs that Memcheck can find</title>

<para>Memcheck is Valgrind's heavyweight memory checking tool.  All
reads and writes of memory are checked, and calls to
malloc/new/free/delete are intercepted. As a result, Memcheck can detect
the following problems:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Use of uninitialised memory</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Reading/writing memory after it has been free'd</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Reading/writing off the end of malloc'd blocks</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Reading/writing inappropriate areas on the stack</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Memory leaks - where pointers to malloc'd blocks are
   lost forever</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Mismatched use of malloc/new/new [] vs
    free/delete/delete []</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Overlapping <computeroutput>src</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> pointers in
    <function>memcpy()</function> and related
    functions</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.flags" 
       xreflabel="Command-line flags specific to Memcheck">
<title>Command-line flags specific to Memcheck</title>

<!-- start of xi:include in the manpage -->
<variablelist id="mc.opts.list">

  <varlistentry id="opt.leak-check" xreflabel="--leak-check">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--leak-check=<no|summary|yes|full> [default: summary] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>When enabled, search for memory leaks when the client
      program finishes.  A memory leak means a malloc'd block, which has
      not yet been free'd, but to which no pointer can be found.  Such a
      block can never be free'd by the program, since no pointer to it
      exists.  If set to <varname>summary</varname>, it says how many
      leaks occurred.  If set to <varname>full</varname> or
      <varname>yes</varname>, it gives details of each individual
      leak.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry id="opt.show-reachable" xreflabel="--show-reachable">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--show-reachable=<yes|no> [default: no] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>When disabled, the memory leak detector only shows blocks
      for which it cannot find a pointer to at all, or it can only find
      a pointer to the middle of.  These blocks are prime candidates for
      memory leaks.  When enabled, the leak detector also reports on
      blocks which it could find a pointer to.  Your program could, at
      least in principle, have freed such blocks before exit.  Contrast
      this to blocks for which no pointer, or only an interior pointer
      could be found: they are more likely to indicate memory leaks,
      because you do not actually have a pointer to the start of the
      block which you can hand to <function>free</function>, even if you
      wanted to.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry id="opt.leak-resolution" xreflabel="--leak-resolution">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--leak-resolution=<low|med|high> [default: low] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>When doing leak checking, determines how willing
      <constant>memcheck</constant> is to consider different backtraces to
      be the same.  When set to <varname>low</varname>, only the first
      two entries need match.  When <varname>med</varname>, four entries
      have to match.  When <varname>high</varname>, all entries need to
      match.</para>

      <para>For hardcore leak debugging, you probably want to use
      <option>--leak-resolution=high</option> together with
      <option>--num-callers=40</option> or some such large number.  Note
      however that this can give an overwhelming amount of information,
      which is why the defaults are 4 callers and low-resolution
      matching.</para>

      <para>Note that the <option>--leak-resolution=</option> setting
      does not affect <constant>memcheck's</constant> ability to find
      leaks.  It only changes how the results are presented.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry id="opt.freelist-vol" xreflabel="--freelist-vol">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--freelist-vol=<number> [default: 5000000] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>When the client program releases memory using
      <function>free</function> (in <literal>C</literal>) or delete
      (<literal>C++</literal>), that memory is not immediately made
      available for re-allocation.  Instead, it is marked inaccessible
      and placed in a queue of freed blocks.  The purpose is to defer as
      long as possible the point at which freed-up memory comes back
      into circulation.  This increases the chance that
      <constant>memcheck</constant> will be able to detect invalid
      accesses to blocks for some significant period of time after they
      have been freed.</para>

      <para>This flag specifies the maximum total size, in bytes, of the
      blocks in the queue.  The default value is five million bytes.
      Increasing this increases the total amount of memory used by
      <constant>memcheck</constant> but may detect invalid uses of freed
      blocks which would otherwise go undetected.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry id="opt.workaround-gcc296-bugs" xreflabel="--workaround-gcc296-bugs">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--workaround-gcc296-bugs=<yes|no> [default: no] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>When enabled, assume that reads and writes some small
      distance below the stack pointer are due to bugs in gcc 2.96, and
      does not report them.  The "small distance" is 256 bytes by
      default.  Note that gcc 2.96 is the default compiler on some older
      Linux distributions (RedHat 7.X) and so you may need to use this
      flag.  Do not use it if you do not have to, as it can cause real
      errors to be overlooked.  A better alternative is to use a more
      recent gcc/g++ in which this bug is fixed.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry id="opt.partial-loads-ok" xreflabel="--partial-loads-ok">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--partial-loads-ok=<yes|no> [default: no] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Controls how <constant>memcheck</constant> handles word-sized,
      word-aligned loads from addresses for which some bytes are
      addressible and others are not.  When <varname>yes</varname>, such
      loads do not elicit an address error.  Instead, the loaded V bytes
      corresponding to the illegal addresses indicate Undefined, and
      those corresponding to legal addresses are loaded from shadow
      memory, as usual.</para>

      <para>When <varname>no</varname>, loads from partially invalid
      addresses are treated the same as loads from completely invalid
      addresses: an illegal-address error is issued, and the resulting V
      bytes indicate valid data.</para>

      <para>Note that code that behaves in this way is in violation of
      the the ISO C/C++ standards, and should be considered broken.  If
      at all possible, such code should be fixed.  This flag should be
      used only as a last resort.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry id="opt.undef-value-errors" xreflabel="--undef-value-errors">
    <term>
      <option><![CDATA[--undef-value-errors=<yes|no> [default: yes] ]]></option>
    </term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Controls whether <constant>memcheck</constant> detects
      dangerous uses of undefined value errors.  Set this to
      <varname>no</varname> if you don't like seeing undefined value
      errors; it also has the side effect of speeding
      <constant>memcheck</constant> up somewhat.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>
<!-- end of xi:include in the manpage -->

</sect1>


<sect1 id="mc-manual.errormsgs"
       xreflabel="Explanation of error messages from Memcheck">
<title>Explanation of error messages from Memcheck</title>

<para>Despite considerable sophistication under the hood, Memcheck can
only really detect two kinds of errors: use of illegal addresses, and
use of undefined values.  Nevertheless, this is enough to help you
discover all sorts of memory-management nasties in your code.  This
section presents a quick summary of what error messages mean.  The
precise behaviour of the error-checking machinery is described in 
<xref linkend="mc-manual.machine"/>.</para>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.badrw" 
       xreflabel="Illegal read / Illegal write errors">
<title>Illegal read / Illegal write errors</title>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Invalid read of size 4
   at 0x40F6BBCC: (within /usr/lib/libpng.so.2.1.0.9)
   by 0x40F6B804: (within /usr/lib/libpng.so.2.1.0.9)
   by 0x40B07FF4: read_png_image__FP8QImageIO (kernel/qpngio.cpp:326)
   by 0x40AC751B: QImageIO::read() (kernel/qimage.cpp:3621)
 Address 0xBFFFF0E0 is not stack'd, malloc'd or free'd
]]></programlisting>

<para>This happens when your program reads or writes memory at a place
which Memcheck reckons it shouldn't.  In this example, the program did a
4-byte read at address 0xBFFFF0E0, somewhere within the system-supplied
library libpng.so.2.1.0.9, which was called from somewhere else in the
same library, called from line 326 of <filename>qpngio.cpp</filename>,
and so on.</para>

<para>Memcheck tries to establish what the illegal address might relate
to, since that's often useful.  So, if it points into a block of memory
which has already been freed, you'll be informed of this, and also where
the block was free'd at.  Likewise, if it should turn out to be just off
the end of a malloc'd block, a common result of off-by-one-errors in
array subscripting, you'll be informed of this fact, and also where the
block was malloc'd.</para>

<para>In this example, Memcheck can't identify the address.  Actually
the address is on the stack, but, for some reason, this is not a valid
stack address -- it is below the stack pointer and that isn't allowed.
In this particular case it's probably caused by gcc generating invalid
code, a known bug in some ancient versions of gcc.</para>

<para>Note that Memcheck only tells you that your program is about to
access memory at an illegal address.  It can't stop the access from
happening.  So, if your program makes an access which normally would
result in a segmentation fault, you program will still suffer the same
fate -- but you will get a message from Memcheck immediately prior to
this.  In this particular example, reading junk on the stack is
non-fatal, and the program stays alive.</para>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="mc-manual.uninitvals" 
       xreflabel="Use of uninitialised values">
<title>Use of uninitialised values</title>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Conditional jump or move depends on uninitialised value(s)
   at 0x402DFA94: _IO_vfprintf (_itoa.h:49)
   by 0x402E8476: _IO_printf (printf.c:36)
   by 0x8048472: main (tests/manuel1.c:8)
]]></programlisting>

<para>An uninitialised-value use error is reported when your program
uses a value which hasn't been initialised -- in other words, is
undefined.  Here, the undefined value is used somewhere inside the
printf() machinery of the C library.  This error was reported when
running the following small program:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
int main()
{
  int x;
  printf ("x = %d\n", x);
}]]></programlisting>

<para>It is important to understand that your program can copy around
junk (uninitialised) data as much as it likes.  Memcheck observes this
and keeps track of the data, but does not complain.  A complaint is
issued only when your program attempts to make use of uninitialised
data.  In this example, x is uninitialised.  Memcheck observes the value
being passed to <literal>_IO_printf</literal> and thence to
<literal>_IO_vfprintf</literal>, but makes no comment.  However,
_IO_vfprintf has to examine the value of x so it can turn it into the
corresponding ASCII string, and it is at this point that Memcheck
complains.</para>

<para>Sources of uninitialised data tend to be:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Local variables in procedures which have not been initialised,
    as in the example above.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The contents of malloc'd blocks, before you write something
    there.  In C++, the new operator is a wrapper round malloc, so if
    you create an object with new, its fields will be uninitialised
    until you (or the constructor) fill them in, which is only Right and
    Proper.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="mc-manual.badfrees" xreflabel="Illegal frees">
<title>Illegal frees</title>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Invalid free()
   at 0x4004FFDF: free (vg_clientmalloc.c:577)
   by 0x80484C7: main (tests/doublefree.c:10)
 Address 0x3807F7B4 is 0 bytes inside a block of size 177 free'd
   at 0x4004FFDF: free (vg_clientmalloc.c:577)
   by 0x80484C7: main (tests/doublefree.c:10)
]]></programlisting>

<para>Memcheck keeps track of the blocks allocated by your program with
malloc/new, so it can know exactly whether or not the argument to
free/delete is legitimate or not.  Here, this test program has freed the
same block twice.  As with the illegal read/write errors, Memcheck
attempts to make sense of the address free'd.  If, as here, the address
is one which has previously been freed, you wil be told that -- making
duplicate frees of the same block easy to spot.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.rudefn" 
       xreflabel="When a block is freed with an inappropriate deallocation
function">
<title>When a block is freed with an inappropriate deallocation
function</title>

<para>In the following example, a block allocated with
<function>new[]</function> has wrongly been deallocated with
<function>free</function>:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Mismatched free() / delete / delete []
   at 0x40043249: free (vg_clientfuncs.c:171)
   by 0x4102BB4E: QGArray::~QGArray(void) (tools/qgarray.cpp:149)
   by 0x4C261C41: PptDoc::~PptDoc(void) (include/qmemarray.h:60)
   by 0x4C261F0E: PptXml::~PptXml(void) (pptxml.cc:44)
 Address 0x4BB292A8 is 0 bytes inside a block of size 64 alloc'd
   at 0x4004318C: __builtin_vec_new (vg_clientfuncs.c:152)
   by 0x4C21BC15: KLaola::readSBStream(int) const (klaola.cc:314)
   by 0x4C21C155: KLaola::stream(KLaola::OLENode const *) (klaola.cc:416)
   by 0x4C21788F: OLEFilter::convert(QCString const &) (olefilter.cc:272)
]]></programlisting>

<para>In <literal>C++</literal> it's important to deallocate memory in a
way compatible with how it was allocated.  The deal is:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>If allocated with
    <function>malloc</function>,
    <function>calloc</function>,
    <function>realloc</function>,
    <function>valloc</function> or
    <function>memalign</function>, you must
    deallocate with <function>free</function>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>If allocated with <function>new[]</function>, you must
    deallocate with <function>delete[]</function>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>If allocated with <function>new</function>, you must deallocate
   with <function>delete</function>.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The worst thing is that on Linux apparently it doesn't matter if
you do muddle these up, and it all seems to work ok, but the same
program may then crash on a different platform, Solaris for example.  So
it's best to fix it properly.  According to the KDE folks "it's amazing
how many C++ programmers don't know this".</para>

<para>Pascal Massimino adds the following clarification:
<function>delete[]</function> must be used for objects allocated by
<function>new[]</function> because the compiler stores the size of the
array and the pointer-to-member to the destructor of the array's content
just before the pointer actually returned.  This implies a
variable-sized overhead in what's returned by <function>new</function>
or <function>new[]</function>.</para>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="mc-manual.badperm" 
       xreflabel="Passing system call parameters with 
       inadequate read/write permissions">
<title>Passing system call parameters with inadequate read/write
permissions</title>

<para>Memcheck checks all parameters to system calls:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>It checks all the direct parameters themselves.</para>
  </listitem> 
  <listitem>
    <para>Also, if a system call needs to read from a buffer provided by
    your program, Memcheck checks that the entire buffer is addressible
    and has valid data, ie, it is readable.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Also, if the system call needs to write to a user-supplied
    buffer, Memcheck checks that the buffer is addressible.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>After the system call, Memcheck updates its tracked information to
precisely reflect any changes in memory permissions caused by the system
call.</para>

<para>Here's an example of two system calls with invalid parameters:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
  #include <stdlib.h>
  #include <unistd.h>
  int main( void )
  {
    char* arr  = malloc(10);
    int*  arr2 = malloc(sizeof(int));
    write( 1 /* stdout */, arr, 10 );
    exit(arr2[0]);
  }
]]></programlisting>

<para>You get these complaints ...</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
  Syscall param write(buf) points to uninitialised byte(s)
     at 0x25A48723: __write_nocancel (in /lib/tls/libc-2.3.3.so)
     by 0x259AFAD3: __libc_start_main (in /lib/tls/libc-2.3.3.so)
     by 0x8048348: (within /auto/homes/njn25/grind/head4/a.out)
   Address 0x25AB8028 is 0 bytes inside a block of size 10 alloc'd
     at 0x259852B0: malloc (vg_replace_malloc.c:130)
     by 0x80483F1: main (a.c:5)

  Syscall param exit(error_code) contains uninitialised byte(s)
     at 0x25A21B44: __GI__exit (in /lib/tls/libc-2.3.3.so)
     by 0x8048426: main (a.c:8)
]]></programlisting>

<para>... because the program has (a) tried to write uninitialised junk
from the malloc'd block to the standard output, and (b) passed an
uninitialised value to <function>exit</function>.  Note that the first
error refers to the memory pointed to by
<computeroutput>buf</computeroutput> (not
<computeroutput>buf</computeroutput> itself), but the second error
refers to the argument <computeroutput>error_code</computeroutput>
itself.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.overlap" 
       xreflabel="Overlapping source and destination blocks">
<title>Overlapping source and destination blocks</title>

<para>The following C library functions copy some data from one
memory block to another (or something similar):
<function>memcpy()</function>,
<function>strcpy()</function>,
<function>strncpy()</function>,
<function>strcat()</function>,
<function>strncat()</function>. 
The blocks pointed to by their <computeroutput>src</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> pointers aren't allowed to overlap.
Memcheck checks for this.</para>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
==27492== Source and destination overlap in memcpy(0xbffff294, 0xbffff280, 21)
==27492==    at 0x40026CDC: memcpy (mc_replace_strmem.c:71)
==27492==    by 0x804865A: main (overlap.c:40)
==27492== 
]]></programlisting>

<para>You don't want the two blocks to overlap because one of them could
get partially trashed by the copying.</para>

<para>You might think that Memcheck is being overly pedantic reporting
this in the case where <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> is less than
<computeroutput>src</computeroutput>.  For example, the obvious way to
implement <function>memcpy()</function> is by copying from the first
byte to the last.  However, the optimisation guides of some
architectures recommend copying from the last byte down to the first.
Also, some implementations of <function>memcpy()</function> zero
<computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> before copying, because zeroing the
destination's cache line(s) can improve performance.</para>

<para>The moral of the story is: if you want to write truly portable
code, don't make any assumptions about the language
implementation.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.leaks" xreflabel="Memory leak detection">
<title>Memory leak detection</title>

<para>Memcheck keeps track of all memory blocks issued in response to
calls to malloc/calloc/realloc/new.  So when the program exits, it knows
which blocks have not been freed.
</para>

<para>If <option>--leak-check</option> is set appropriately, for each
remaining block, Memcheck scans the entire address space of the process,
looking for pointers to the block.  Each block fits into one of the
three following categories.</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>Still reachable: A pointer to the start of the block is found.
    This usually indicates programming sloppiness.  Since the block is
    still pointed at, the programmer could, at least in principle, free
    it before program exit.  Because these are very common and arguably
    not a problem, Memcheck won't report such blocks unless
    <option>--show-reachable=yes</option> is specified.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Possibly lost, or "dubious": A pointer to the interior of the
    block is found.  The pointer might originally have pointed to the
    start and have been moved along, or it might be entirely unrelated.
    Memcheck deems such a block as "dubious", because it's unclear
    whether or not a pointer to it still exists.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Definitely lost, or "leaked": The worst outcome is that no
    pointer to the block can be found.  The block is classified as
    "leaked", because the programmer could not possibly have freed it at
    program exit, since no pointer to it exists.  This is likely a
    symptom of having lost the pointer at some earlier point in the
    program.</para>
    </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>For each block mentioned, Memcheck will also tell you where the
block was allocated.  It cannot tell you how or why the pointer to a
leaked block has been lost; you have to work that out for yourself.  In
general, you should attempt to ensure your programs do not have any
leaked or dubious blocks at exit.</para>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
8 bytes in 1 blocks are definitely lost in loss record 1 of 14
   at 0x........: malloc (vg_replace_malloc.c:...)
   by 0x........: mk (leak-tree.c:11)
   by 0x........: main (leak-tree.c:39)

88 (8 direct, 80 indirect) bytes in 1 blocks are definitely lost 
                           in loss record 13 of 14
   at 0x........: malloc (vg_replace_malloc.c:...)
   by 0x........: mk (leak-tree.c:11)
   by 0x........: main (leak-tree.c:25)
]]></programlisting>

<para>The first message describes a simple case of a single 8 byte block
that has been definitely lost.  The second case mentions both "direct"
and "indirect" leaks.  The distinction is that a direct leak is a block
which has no pointers to it.  An indirect leak is a block which is only
pointed to by other leaked blocks.  Both kinds of leak are bad.</para>

<para>The precise area of memory in which Memcheck searches for pointers
is: all naturally-aligned machine-word-sized words for which all A bits
indicate addressibility and all V bits indicated that the stored value
is actually valid.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.suppfiles" xreflabel="Writing suppression files">
<title>Writing suppression files</title>

<para>The basic suppression format is described in 
<xref linkend="manual-core.suppress"/>.</para>

<para>The suppression (2nd) line should have the form:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Memcheck:suppression_type]]></programlisting>

<para>The Memcheck suppression types are as follows:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para><varname>Value1</varname>, 
    <varname>Value2</varname>,
    <varname>Value4</varname>,
    <varname>Value8</varname>,
    <varname>Value16</varname>,
    meaning an uninitialised-value error when
    using a value of 1, 2, 4, 8 or 16 bytes.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Cond</varname> (or its old
    name, <varname>Value0</varname>), meaning use
    of an uninitialised CPU condition code.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Addr1</varname>,
    <varname>Addr2</varname>, 
    <varname>Addr4</varname>,
    <varname>Addr8</varname>,
    <varname>Addr16</varname>, 
    meaning an invalid address during a
    memory access of 1, 2, 4, 8 or 16 bytes respectively.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Jump</varname>, meaning an
    jump to an unaddressable location error.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Param</varname>, meaning an
    invalid system call parameter error.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Free</varname>, meaning an
    invalid or mismatching free.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Overlap</varname>, meaning a
    <computeroutput>src</computeroutput> /
    <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> overlap in
    <function>memcpy()</function> or a similar function.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <varname>Leak</varname>, meaning
    a memory leak.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>The extra information line: for Param errors, is the name of the
offending system call parameter.  No other error kinds have this extra
line.</para>

<para>The first line of the calling context: for Value and Addr errors,
it is either the name of the function in which the error occurred, or,
failing that, the full path of the .so file or executable containing the
error location.  For Free errors, is the name of the function doing the
freeing (eg, <function>free</function>,
<function>__builtin_vec_delete</function>, etc).  For Overlap errors, is
the name of the function with the overlapping arguments (eg.
<function>memcpy()</function>, <function>strcpy()</function>,
etc).</para>

<para>Lastly, there's the rest of the calling context.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.machine" 
       xreflabel="Details of Memcheck's checking machinery">
<title>Details of Memcheck's checking machinery</title>

<para>Read this section if you want to know, in detail, exactly
what and how Memcheck is checking.</para>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.value" xreflabel="Valid-value (V) bit">
<title>Valid-value (V) bits</title>

<para>It is simplest to think of Memcheck implementing a synthetic CPU
which is identical to a real CPU, except for one crucial detail.  Every
bit (literally) of data processed, stored and handled by the real CPU
has, in the synthetic CPU, an associated "valid-value" bit, which says
whether or not the accompanying bit has a legitimate value.  In the
discussions which follow, this bit is referred to as the V (valid-value)
bit.</para>

<para>Each byte in the system therefore has a 8 V bits which follow it
wherever it goes.  For example, when the CPU loads a word-size item (4
bytes) from memory, it also loads the corresponding 32 V bits from a
bitmap which stores the V bits for the process' entire address space.
If the CPU should later write the whole or some part of that value to
memory at a different address, the relevant V bits will be stored back
in the V-bit bitmap.</para>

<para>In short, each bit in the system has an associated V bit, which
follows it around everywhere, even inside the CPU.  Yes, all the CPU's
registers (integer, floating point, vector and condition registers) have
their own V bit vectors.</para>

<para>Copying values around does not cause Memcheck to check for, or
report on, errors.  However, when a value is used in a way which might
conceivably affect the outcome of your program's computation, the
associated V bits are immediately checked.  If any of these indicate
that the value is undefined, an error is reported.</para>

<para>Here's an (admittedly nonsensical) example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
int i, j;
int a[10], b[10];
for ( i = 0; i < 10; i++ ) {
  j = a[i];
  b[i] = j;
}]]></programlisting>

<para>Memcheck emits no complaints about this, since it merely copies
uninitialised values from <varname>a[]</varname> into
<varname>b[]</varname>, and doesn't use them in any way.  However, if
the loop is changed to:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
for ( i = 0; i < 10; i++ ) {
  j += a[i];
}
if ( j == 77 ) 
  printf("hello there\n");
]]></programlisting>

<para>then Valgrind will complain, at the
<computeroutput>if</computeroutput>, that the condition depends on
uninitialised values.  Note that it <command>doesn't</command> complain
at the <varname>j += a[i];</varname>, since at that point the
undefinedness is not "observable".  It's only when a decision has to be
made as to whether or not to do the <function>printf</function> -- an
observable action of your program -- that Memcheck complains.</para>

<para>Most low level operations, such as adds, cause Memcheck to use the
V bits for the operands to calculate the V bits for the result.  Even if
the result is partially or wholly undefined, it does not
complain.</para>

<para>Checks on definedness only occur in three places: when a value is
used to generate a memory address, when control flow decision needs to
be made, and when a system call is detected, Valgrind checks definedness
of parameters as required.</para>

<para>If a check should detect undefinedness, an error message is
issued.  The resulting value is subsequently regarded as well-defined.
To do otherwise would give long chains of error messages.  In effect, we
say that undefined values are non-infectious.</para>

<para>This sounds overcomplicated.  Why not just check all reads from
memory, and complain if an undefined value is loaded into a CPU
register?  Well, that doesn't work well, because perfectly legitimate C
programs routinely copy uninitialised values around in memory, and we
don't want endless complaints about that.  Here's the canonical example.
Consider a struct like this:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
struct S { int x; char c; };
struct S s1, s2;
s1.x = 42;
s1.c = 'z';
s2 = s1;
]]></programlisting>

<para>The question to ask is: how large is <varname>struct S</varname>,
in bytes?  An <varname>int</varname> is 4 bytes and a
<varname>char</varname> one byte, so perhaps a <varname>struct
S</varname> occupies 5 bytes?  Wrong.  All (non-toy) compilers we know
of will round the size of <varname>struct S</varname> up to a whole
number of words, in this case 8 bytes.  Not doing this forces compilers
to generate truly appalling code for subscripting arrays of
<varname>struct S</varname>'s.</para>

<para>So <varname>s1</varname> occupies 8 bytes, yet only 5 of them will
be initialised.  For the assignment <varname>s2 = s1</varname>, gcc
generates code to copy all 8 bytes wholesale into <varname>s2</varname>
without regard for their meaning.  If Memcheck simply checked values as
they came out of memory, it would yelp every time a structure assignment
like this happened.  So the more complicated semantics described above
is necessary.  This allows <literal>gcc</literal> to copy
<varname>s1</varname> into <varname>s2</varname> any way it likes, and a
warning will only be emitted if the uninitialised values are later
used.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.vaddress" xreflabel=" Valid-address (A) bits">
<title>Valid-address (A) bits</title>

<para>Notice that the previous subsection describes how the validity of
values is established and maintained without having to say whether the
program does or does not have the right to access any particular memory
location.  We now consider the latter issue.</para>

<para>As described above, every bit in memory or in the CPU has an
associated valid-value (V) bit.  In addition, all bytes in memory, but
not in the CPU, have an associated valid-address (A) bit.  This
indicates whether or not the program can legitimately read or write that
location.  It does not give any indication of the validity or the data
at that location -- that's the job of the V bits -- only whether or not
the location may be accessed.</para>

<para>Every time your program reads or writes memory, Memcheck checks
the A bits associated with the address.  If any of them indicate an
invalid address, an error is emitted.  Note that the reads and writes
themselves do not change the A bits, only consult them.</para>

<para>So how do the A bits get set/cleared?  Like this:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>When the program starts, all the global data areas are
    marked as accessible.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When the program does malloc/new, the A bits for exactly the
    area allocated, and not a byte more, are marked as accessible.  Upon
    freeing the area the A bits are changed to indicate
    inaccessibility.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When the stack pointer register (<literal>SP</literal>) moves
    up or down, A bits are set.  The rule is that the area from
    <literal>SP</literal> up to the base of the stack is marked as
    accessible, and below <literal>SP</literal> is inaccessible.  (If
    that sounds illogical, bear in mind that the stack grows down, not
    up, on almost all Unix systems, including GNU/Linux.)  Tracking
    <literal>SP</literal> like this has the useful side-effect that the
    section of stack used by a function for local variables etc is
    automatically marked accessible on function entry and inaccessible
    on exit.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When doing system calls, A bits are changed appropriately.
    For example, mmap() magically makes files appear in the process'
    address space, so the A bits must be updated if mmap()
    succeeds.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Optionally, your program can tell Valgrind about such changes
    explicitly, using the client request mechanism described
    above.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.together" xreflabel="Putting it all together">
<title>Putting it all together</title>

<para>Memcheck's checking machinery can be summarised as
follows:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Each byte in memory has 8 associated V (valid-value) bits,
    saying whether or not the byte has a defined value, and a single A
    (valid-address) bit, saying whether or not the program currently has
    the right to read/write that address.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When memory is read or written, the relevant A bits are
    consulted.  If they indicate an invalid address, Valgrind emits an
    Invalid read or Invalid write error.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When memory is read into the CPU's registers, the relevant V
    bits are fetched from memory and stored in the simulated CPU.  They
    are not consulted.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When a register is written out to memory, the V bits for that
    register are written back to memory too.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When values in CPU registers are used to generate a memory
    address, or to determine the outcome of a conditional branch, the V
    bits for those values are checked, and an error emitted if any of
    them are undefined.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When values in CPU registers are used for any other purpose,
    Valgrind computes the V bits for the result, but does not check
    them.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>One the V bits for a value in the CPU have been checked, they
    are then set to indicate validity.  This avoids long chains of
    errors.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When values are loaded from memory, valgrind checks the A bits
    for that location and issues an illegal-address warning if needed.
    In that case, the V bits loaded are forced to indicate Valid,
    despite the location being invalid.</para>

    <para>This apparently strange choice reduces the amount of confusing
    information presented to the user.  It avoids the unpleasant
    phenomenon in which memory is read from a place which is both
    unaddressible and contains invalid values, and, as a result, you get
    not only an invalid-address (read/write) error, but also a
    potentially large set of uninitialised-value errors, one for every
    time the value is used.</para>

    <para>There is a hazy boundary case to do with multi-byte loads from
    addresses which are partially valid and partially invalid.  See
    details of the flag <option>--partial-loads-ok</option> for details.
    </para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>


<para>Memcheck intercepts calls to malloc, calloc, realloc, valloc,
memalign, free, new, new[], delete and delete[].  The behaviour you get
is:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>malloc/new/new[]: the returned memory is marked as addressible
    but not having valid values.  This means you have to write on it
    before you can read it.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>calloc: returned memory is marked both addressible and valid,
    since calloc() clears the area to zero.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>realloc: if the new size is larger than the old, the new
    section is addressible but invalid, as with malloc.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>If the new size is smaller, the dropped-off section is marked
    as unaddressible.  You may only pass to realloc a pointer previously
    issued to you by malloc/calloc/realloc.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>free/delete/delete[]: you may only pass to these functions a
    pointer previously issued to you by the corresponding allocation
    function.  Otherwise, Valgrind complains.  If the pointer is indeed
    valid, Valgrind marks the entire area it points at as unaddressible,
    and places the block in the freed-blocks-queue.  The aim is to defer
    as long as possible reallocation of this block.  Until that happens,
    all attempts to access it will elicit an invalid-address error, as
    you would hope.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.clientreqs" xreflabel="Client requests">
<title>Client Requests</title>

<para>The following client requests are defined in
<filename>memcheck.h</filename>.
See <filename>memcheck.h</filename> for exact details of their
arguments.</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MAKE_MEM_NOACCESS</varname>,
    <varname>VALGRIND_MAKE_MEM_UNDEFINED</varname> and
    <varname>VALGRIND_MAKE_MEM_DEFINED</varname>.
    These mark address ranges as completely inaccessible,
    accessible but containing undefined data, and accessible and
    containing defined data, respectively.  Subsequent errors may
    have their faulting addresses described in terms of these
    blocks.  Returns a "block handle".  Returns zero when not run
    on Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MAKE_MEM_DEFINED_IF_ADDRESSABLE</varname>.
    This is just like <varname>VALGRIND_MAKE_MEM_DEFINED</varname> but only
    affects those bytes that are already addressable.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_DISCARD</varname>: At some point you may
    want Valgrind to stop reporting errors in terms of the blocks
    defined by the previous three macros.  To do this, the above macros
    return a small-integer "block handle".  You can pass this block
    handle to <varname>VALGRIND_DISCARD</varname>.  After doing so,
    Valgrind will no longer be able to relate addressing errors to the
    user-defined block associated with the handle.  The permissions
    settings associated with the handle remain in place; this just
    affects how errors are reported, not whether they are reported.
    Returns 1 for an invalid handle and 0 for a valid handle (although
    passing invalid handles is harmless).  Always returns 0 when not run
    on Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_CHECK_MEM_IS_ADDRESSABLE</varname> and
    <varname>VALGRIND_CHECK_MEM_IS_DEFINED</varname>: check immediately
    whether or not the given address range has the relevant property,
    and if not, print an error message.  Also, for the convenience of
    the client, returns zero if the relevant property holds; otherwise,
    the returned value is the address of the first byte for which the
    property is not true.  Always returns 0 when not run on
    Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_CHECK_VALUE_IS_DEFINED</varname>: a quick and easy
    way to find out whether Valgrind thinks a particular value
    (lvalue, to be precise) is addressable and defined.  Prints an error
    message if not.  Returns no value.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_DO_LEAK_CHECK</varname>: run the memory leak
    detector right now.  Returns no value.  I guess this could be used
    to incrementally check for leaks between arbitrary places in the
    program's execution.  Warning: not properly tested!</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_COUNT_LEAKS</varname>: fills in the four
    arguments with the number of bytes of memory found by the previous
    leak check to be leaked, dubious, reachable and suppressed.  Again,
    useful in test harness code, after calling
    <varname>VALGRIND_DO_LEAK_CHECK</varname>.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_GET_VBITS</varname> and
    <varname>VALGRIND_SET_VBITS</varname>: allow you to get and set the
    V (validity) bits for an address range.  You should probably only
    set V bits that you have got with
    <varname>VALGRIND_GET_VBITS</varname>.  Only for those who really
    know what they are doing.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>




<sect1 id="mc-manual.mempools" xreflabel="Memory pools">
<title>Memory Pools: describing and working with custom allocators</title>

<para>Some programs use custom memory allocators, often for performance
reasons.  Left to itself, Memcheck is unable to "understand" the
behaviour of custom allocation schemes and so may miss errors and
leaks in your program.  What this section describes is a way to give
Memcheck enough of a description of your custom allocator that it can
make at least some sense of what is happening.</para>

<para>There are many different sorts of custom allocator, so Memcheck
attempts to reason about them using a loose, abstract model.  We
use the following terminology when describing custom allocation
systems:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Custom allocation involves a set of independent "memory pools".
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Memcheck's notion of a a memory pool consists of a single "anchor
    address" and a set of non-overlapping "chunks" associated with the
    anchor address.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Typically a pool's anchor address is the address of a 
    book-keeping "header" structure.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Typically the pool's chunks are drawn from a contiguous
    "superblock" acquired through the system malloc() or mmap().</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>Keep in mind that the last two points above say "typically": the
Valgrind mempool client request API is intentionally vague about the
exact structure of a mempool. There is no specific mention made of
headers or superblocks. Nevertheless, the following picture may help
elucidate the intention of the terms in the API:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
   "pool"
   (anchor address)
   |
   v
   +--------+---+
   | header | o |
   +--------+-|-+
              |
              v                  superblock
              +------+---+--------------+---+------------------+
              |      |rzB|  allocation  |rzB|                  |
              +------+---+--------------+---+------------------+
                         ^              ^
                         |              |
                       "addr"     "addr"+"size"
]]></programlisting>

<para>
Note that the header and the superblock may be contiguous or
discontiguous, and there may be multiple superblocks associated with a
single header; such variations are opaque to Memcheck. The API
only requires that your allocation scheme can present sensible values
of "pool", "addr" and "size".</para>

<para>
Typically, before making client requests related to mempools, a client
program will have allocated such a header and superblock for their
mempool, and marked the superblock NOACCESS using the
<varname>VALGRIND_MAKE_MEM_NOACCESS</varname> client request.</para>

<para>
When dealing with mempools, the goal is to maintain a particular
invariant condition: that Memcheck believes the unallocated portions
of the pool's superblock (including redzones) are NOACCESS. To
maintain this invariant, the client program must ensure that the
superblock starts out in that state; Memcheck cannot make it so, since
Memcheck never explicitly learns about the superblock of a pool, only
the allocated chunks within the pool.</para>

<para>
Once the header and superblock for a pool are established and properly
marked, there are a number of client requests programs can use to
inform Memcheck about changes to the state of a mempool:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>
    <varname>VALGRIND_CREATE_MEMPOOL(pool, rzB, is_zeroed)</varname>:
    This request registers the address "pool" as the anchor address 
    for a memory pool. It also provides a size "rzB", specifying how 
    large the redzones placed around chunks allocated from the pool 
    should be. Finally, it provides an "is_zeroed" flag that specifies 
    whether the pool's chunks are zeroed (more precisely: defined) 
    when allocated.
    </para>
    <para>
    Upon completion of this request, no chunks are associated with the
    pool.  The request simply tells Memcheck that the pool exists, so that
    subsequent calls can refer to it as a pool.
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_DESTROY_MEMPOOL(pool)</varname>:
    This request tells Memcheck that a pool is being torn down. Memcheck
    then removes all records of chunks associated with the pool, as well
    as its record of the pool's existence. While destroying its records of
    a mempool, Memcheck resets the redzones of any live chunks in the pool
    to NOACCESS.
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_ALLOC(pool, addr, size)</varname>:
    This request informs Memcheck that a "size"-byte chunk has been
    allocated at "addr", and associates the chunk with the specified
    "pool". If the pool was created with nonzero "rzB" redzones, Memcheck
    will mark the "rzB" bytes before and after the chunk as NOACCESS. If
    the pool was created with the "is_zeroed" flag set, Memcheck will mark
    the chunk as DEFINED, otherwise Memcheck will mark the chunk as
    UNDEFINED.
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_FREE(pool, addr)</varname>:
    This request informs Memcheck that the chunk at "addr" should no
    longer be considered allocated. Memcheck will mark the chunk
    associated with "addr" as NOACCESS, and delete its record of the
    chunk's existence.
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_TRIM(pool, addr, size)</varname>:
    This request "trims" the chunks associated with "pool". The request
    only operates on chunks associated with "pool". Trimming is formally
    defined as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> All chunks entirely inside the range [addr,addr+size) are
        preserved.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All chunks entirely outside the range [addr,addr+size) are
        discarded, as though <varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_FREE</varname>
        was called on them. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>All other chunks must intersect with the range 
        [addr,addr+size); areas outside the intersection are marked as 
        NOACCESS, as though they had been independently freed with 
        <varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_FREE</varname>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This is a somewhat rare request, but can be useful in 
    implementing the type of mass-free operations common in custom 
    LIFO allocators.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MOVE_MEMPOOL(poolA, poolB)</varname>:
    This request informs Memcheck that the pool previously anchored at
    address "poolA" has moved to anchor address "poolB". This is a rare
    request, typically only needed if you realloc() the header of 
    a mempool.</para>
    <para>No memory-status bits are altered by this request.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>
    <varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_CHANGE(pool, addrA, addrB, size)</varname>:
    This request informs Memcheck that the chunk previously allocated at
    address "addrA" within "pool" has been moved and/or resized, and should
    be changed to cover the region [addrB,addrB+size). This is a rare
    request, typically only needed if you realloc() a superblock or wish
    to extend a chunk without changing its memory-status bits.
    </para>
    <para>No memory-status bits are altered by this request.
    </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><varname>VALGRIND_MEMPOOL_EXISTS(pool)</varname>:
    This request informs the caller whether or not Memcheck is currently 
    tracking a mempool at anchor address "pool". It evaluates to 1 when 
    there is a mempool associated with that address, 0 otherwise. This is a 
    rare request, only useful in circumstances when client code might have 
    lost track of the set of active mempools.
    </para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>


</sect1>
</chapter>
