<?xml version="1.0"?> <!-- -*- sgml -*- -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="mc-manual" xreflabel="Memcheck: a heavyweight memory checker">
<title>Memcheck: a heavyweight memory checker</title>

<para>To use this tool, you must specify
<computeroutput>--tool=memcheck</computeroutput> on the Valgrind
command line.</para>


<sect1 id="mc-manual.bugs" 
       xreflabel="Kinds of bugs that Memcheck can find">
<title>Kinds of bugs that Memcheck can find</title>

<para>Memcheck is Valgrind-1.0.X's checking mechanism bundled up
into a tool.  All reads and writes of memory are checked, and
calls to malloc/new/free/delete are intercepted. As a result,
Memcheck can detect the following problems:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Use of uninitialised memory</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Reading/writing memory after it has been free'd</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Reading/writing off the end of malloc'd blocks</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Reading/writing inappropriate areas on the stack</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Memory leaks -- where pointers to malloc'd blocks are
   lost forever</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Mismatched use of malloc/new/new [] vs
    free/delete/delete []</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Overlapping <computeroutput>src</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> pointers in
    <computeroutput>memcpy()</computeroutput> and related
    functions</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Some misuses of the POSIX pthreads API</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.flags" 
       xreflabel="Command-line flags specific to Memcheck">
<title>Command-line flags specific to Memcheck</title>

<itemizedlist id="leakcheck">
  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>--leak-check=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--leak-check=summary</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--leak-check=full</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, search for memory leaks when the client
    program finishes.  A memory leak means a malloc'd block,
    which has not yet been free'd, but to which no pointer can be
    found.  Such a block can never be free'd by the program,
    since no pointer to it exists.  If set to
    <computeroutput>summary</computeroutput>, it says how many leaks occurred.
    If set to <computeroutput>all</computeroutput>, it gives details of each
    individual leak.</para>

  </listitem>

  <listitem id="showreach">
    <para><computeroutput>--show-reachable=no</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--show-reachable=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When disabled, the memory leak detector only shows
    blocks for which it cannot find a pointer to at all, or it
    can only find a pointer to the middle of.  These blocks are
    prime candidates for memory leaks.  When enabled, the leak
    detector also reports on blocks which it could find a pointer
    to.  Your program could, at least in principle, have freed
    such blocks before exit.  Contrast this to blocks for which
    no pointer, or only an interior pointer could be found: they
    are more likely to indicate memory leaks, because you do not
    actually have a pointer to the start of the block which you
    can hand to <computeroutput>free</computeroutput>, even if
    you wanted to.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="leakres">
    <para><computeroutput>--leak-resolution=low</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--leak-resolution=med</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--leak-resolution=high</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When doing leak checking, determines how willing
    Memcheck is to consider different backtraces to be the same.
    When set to <computeroutput>low</computeroutput>, the
    default, only the first two entries need match.  When
    <computeroutput>med</computeroutput>, four entries have to
    match.  When <computeroutput>high</computeroutput>, all
    entries need to match.</para>
    <para>For hardcore leak debugging, you probably want to use
    <computeroutput>--leak-resolution=high</computeroutput>
    together with
    <computeroutput>--num-callers=40</computeroutput> or some
    such large number.  Note however that this can give an
    overwhelming amount of information, which is why the defaults
    are 4 callers and low-resolution matching.</para>
    <para>Note that the
    <computeroutput>--leak-resolution=</computeroutput> setting
    does not affect Memcheck's ability to find leaks.  It only
    changes how the results are presented.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="freelist">
    <para><computeroutput>--freelist-vol=&lt;number></computeroutput>
    [default: 1000000]</para>
    <para>When the client program releases memory using free (in
    <literal>C</literal>) or delete (<literal>C++</literal>),
    that memory is not immediately made available for
    re-allocation.  Instead it is marked inaccessible and placed
    in a queue of freed blocks.  The purpose is to delay the
    point at which freed-up memory comes back into circulation.
    This increases the chance that Memcheck will be able to
    detect invalid accesses to blocks for some significant period
    of time after they have been freed.</para>
    <para>This flag specifies the maximum total size, in bytes,
    of the blocks in the queue.  The default value is one million
    bytes.  Increasing this increases the total amount of memory
    used by Memcheck but may detect invalid uses of freed blocks
    which would otherwise go undetected.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="gcc296">
    <para><computeroutput>--workaround-gcc296-bugs=no</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--workaround-gcc296-bugs=yes</computeroutput></para>
    <para>When enabled, assume that reads and writes some small
    distance below the stack pointer
    <computeroutput>%esp</computeroutput> are due to bugs in gcc
    2.96, and does not report them.  The "small distance" is 256
    bytes by default.  Note that gcc 2.96 is the default compiler
    on some popular Linux distributions (RedHat 7.X, Mandrake)
    and so you may well need to use this flag.  Do not use it if
    you do not have to, as it can cause real errors to be
    overlooked.  Another option is to use a gcc/g++ which does
    not generate accesses below the stack pointer.  2.95.3 seems
    to be a good choice in this respect.</para>
    <para>Unfortunately (27 Feb 02) it looks like g++ 3.0.4 has a
    similar bug, so you may need to issue this flag if you use
    3.0.4.  A while later (early Apr 02) this is confirmed as a
    scheduling bug in g++-3.0.4.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="partial">
    <para><computeroutput>--partial-loads-ok=yes</computeroutput>
    [default]</para>
    <para><computeroutput>--partial-loads-ok=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para>Controls how Memcheck handles word (4-byte) loads from
    addresses for which some bytes are addressible and others are
    not.  When <computeroutput>yes</computeroutput> (the
    default), such loads do not elicit an address error.
    Instead, the loaded V bytes corresponding to the illegal
    addresses indicate undefined, and those corresponding to
    legal addresses are loaded from shadow memory, as usual.</para>
    <para>When <computeroutput>no</computeroutput>, loads from
    partially invalid addresses are treated the same as loads
    from completely invalid addresses: an illegal-address error
    is issued, and the resulting V bytes indicate valid data.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem id="strlen">
    <para><computeroutput>--avoid-strlen-errors=no</computeroutput></para>
    <para><computeroutput>--avoid-strlen-errors=yes</computeroutput> [default]</para>
    <para>Enable or disable a heuristic for dealing with highly-optimized 
    versions of strlen.  These versions of strlen can cause spurious errors 
    to be reported by Memcheck, so it's usually a good idea to leave this
    enabled.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="mc-manual.errormsgs"
       xreflabel="Explanation of error messages from Memcheck">
<title>Explanation of error messages from Memcheck</title>

<para>Despite considerable sophistication under the hood,
Memcheck can only really detect two kinds of errors, use of
illegal addresses, and use of undefined values.  Nevertheless,
this is enough to help you discover all sorts of
memory-management nasties in your code.  This section presents a
quick summary of what error messages mean.  The precise behaviour
of the error-checking machinery is described in <xref
linkend="mc-manual.machine"/>.</para>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.badrw" 
       xreflabel="Illegal read / Illegal write errors">
<title>Illegal read / Illegal write errors</title>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Invalid read of size 4
   at 0x40F6BBCC: (within /usr/lib/libpng.so.2.1.0.9)
   by 0x40F6B804: (within /usr/lib/libpng.so.2.1.0.9)
   by 0x40B07FF4: read_png_image__FP8QImageIO (kernel/qpngio.cpp:326)
   by 0x40AC751B: QImageIO::read() (kernel/qimage.cpp:3621)
 Address 0xBFFFF0E0 is not stack'd, malloc'd or free'd
]]></programlisting>

<para>This happens when your program reads or writes memory at a
place which Memcheck reckons it shouldn't.  In this example, the
program did a 4-byte read at address 0xBFFFF0E0, somewhere within
the system-supplied library libpng.so.2.1.0.9, which was called
from somewhere else in the same library, called from line 326 of
<filename>qpngio.cpp</filename>, and so on.</para>

<para>Memcheck tries to establish what the illegal address might
relate to, since that's often useful.  So, if it points into a
block of memory which has already been freed, you'll be informed
of this, and also where the block was free'd at.  Likewise, if it
should turn out to be just off the end of a malloc'd block, a
common result of off-by-one-errors in array subscripting, you'll
be informed of this fact, and also where the block was
malloc'd.</para>

<para>In this example, Memcheck can't identify the address.
Actually the address is on the stack, but, for some reason, this
is not a valid stack address -- it is below the stack pointer,
<literal>%esp</literal>, and that isn't allowed.  In this
particular case it's probably caused by gcc generating invalid
code, a known bug in various flavours of gcc.</para>

<para>Note that Memcheck only tells you that your program is
about to access memory at an illegal address.  It can't stop the
access from happening.  So, if your program makes an access which
normally would result in a segmentation fault, you program will
still suffer the same fate -- but you will get a message from
Memcheck immediately prior to this.  In this particular example,
reading junk on the stack is non-fatal, and the program stays
alive.</para>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="mc-manual.uninitvals" 
       xreflabel="Use of uninitialised values">
<title>Use of uninitialised values</title>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Conditional jump or move depends on uninitialised value(s)
   at 0x402DFA94: _IO_vfprintf (_itoa.h:49)
   by 0x402E8476: _IO_printf (printf.c:36)
   by 0x8048472: main (tests/manuel1.c:8)
]]></programlisting>

<para>An uninitialised-value use error is reported when your
program uses a value which hasn't been initialised -- in other
words, is undefined.  Here, the undefined value is used somewhere
inside the printf() machinery of the C library.  This error was
reported when running the following small program:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
int main()
{
  int x;
  printf ("x = %d\n", x);
}]]></programlisting>

<para>It is important to understand that your program can copy
around junk (uninitialised) data to its heart's content.
Memcheck observes this and keeps track of the data, but does not
complain.  A complaint is issued only when your program attempts
to make use of uninitialised data.  In this example, x is
uninitialised.  Memcheck observes the value being passed to
<literal>_IO_printf</literal> and thence to
<literal>_IO_vfprintf</literal>, but makes no comment.  However,
_IO_vfprintf has to examine the value of x so it can turn it into
the corresponding ASCII string, and it is at this point that
Memcheck complains.</para>

<para>Sources of uninitialised data tend to be:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Local variables in procedures which have not been
    initialised, as in the example above.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The contents of malloc'd blocks, before you write
    something there.  In C++, the new operator is a wrapper round
    malloc, so if you create an object with new, its fields will
    be uninitialised until you (or the constructor) fill them in,
    which is only Right and Proper.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>



<sect2 id="mc-manual.badfrees" xreflabel="Illegal frees">
<title>Illegal frees</title>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Invalid free()
   at 0x4004FFDF: free (vg_clientmalloc.c:577)
   by 0x80484C7: main (tests/doublefree.c:10)
 Address 0x3807F7B4 is 0 bytes inside a block of size 177 free'd
   at 0x4004FFDF: free (vg_clientmalloc.c:577)
   by 0x80484C7: main (tests/doublefree.c:10)
]]></programlisting>

<para>Memcheck keeps track of the blocks allocated by your
program with malloc/new, so it can know exactly whether or not
the argument to free/delete is legitimate or not.  Here, this
test program has freed the same block twice.  As with the illegal
read/write errors, Memcheck attempts to make sense of the address
free'd.  If, as here, the address is one which has previously
been freed, you wil be told that -- making duplicate frees of the
same block easy to spot.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.rudefn" 
       xreflabel="When a block is freed with an inappropriate deallocation
function">
<title>When a block is freed with an inappropriate deallocation
function</title>

<para>In the following example, a block allocated with
<computeroutput>new[]</computeroutput> has wrongly been
deallocated with <computeroutput>free</computeroutput>:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Mismatched free() / delete / delete []
   at 0x40043249: free (vg_clientfuncs.c:171)
   by 0x4102BB4E: QGArray::~QGArray(void) (tools/qgarray.cpp:149)
   by 0x4C261C41: PptDoc::~PptDoc(void) (include/qmemarray.h:60)
   by 0x4C261F0E: PptXml::~PptXml(void) (pptxml.cc:44)
 Address 0x4BB292A8 is 0 bytes inside a block of size 64 alloc'd
   at 0x4004318C: __builtin_vec_new (vg_clientfuncs.c:152)
   by 0x4C21BC15: KLaola::readSBStream(int) const (klaola.cc:314)
   by 0x4C21C155: KLaola::stream(KLaola::OLENode const *) (klaola.cc:416)
   by 0x4C21788F: OLEFilter::convert(QCString const &) (olefilter.cc:272)
]]></programlisting>

<para>The following was told to me be the KDE 3 developers.  I
didn't know any of it myself.  They also implemented the check
itself.</para>

<para>In <literal>C++</literal> it's important to deallocate
memory in a way compatible with how it was allocated.  The deal
is:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>If allocated with
    <computeroutput>malloc</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>calloc</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>realloc</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>valloc</computeroutput> or
    <computeroutput>memalign</computeroutput>, you must
    deallocate with <computeroutput>free</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>If allocated with
    <computeroutput>new[]</computeroutput>, you must deallocate
    with <computeroutput>delete[]</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>If allocated with <computeroutput>new</computeroutput>,
   you must deallocate with
   <computeroutput>delete</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The worst thing is that on Linux apparently it doesn't
matter if you do muddle these up, and it all seems to work ok,
but the same program may then crash on a different platform,
Solaris for example.  So it's best to fix it properly.  According
to the KDE folks "it's amazing how many C++ programmers don't
know this".</para>

<para>Pascal Massimino adds the following clarification:
<computeroutput>delete[]</computeroutput> must be called
associated with a <computeroutput>new[]</computeroutput> because
the compiler stores the size of the array and the
pointer-to-member to the destructor of the array's content just
before the pointer actually returned.  This implies a
variable-sized overhead in what's returned by
<computeroutput>new</computeroutput> or
<computeroutput>new[]</computeroutput>.</para>
</sect2>



<sect2 id="mc-manual.badperm" 
       xreflabel="Passing system call parameters with 
       inadequate read/write permissions">
<title>Passing system call parameters with inadequate read/write
permissions</title>

<para>Memcheck checks all parameters to system calls, i.e:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>It checks all the direct parameters
  themselves.</para></listitem> 
  <listitem><para>Also, if a system call needs to read from a buffer provided
  by your program, Memcheck checks that the entire buffer is addressible and
  has valid data, ie, it is readable.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Also, if the system call needs to write to a user-supplied
  buffer, Memcheck checks that the buffer is addressible.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>After the system call, Memcheck updates its tracked information to
precisely reflect any changes in memory permissions caused by the system call.
</para>

<para>Here's an example of two system calls with invalid parameters:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
  #include <stdlib.h>
  #include <unistd.h>
  int main( void )
  {
    char* arr  = malloc(10);
    int*  arr2 = malloc(sizeof(int));
    write( 1 /* stdout */, arr, 10 );
    exit(arr2[0]);
  }
]]></programlisting>

<para>You get these complaints ...</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
  Syscall param write(buf) points to uninitialised byte(s)
     at 0x25A48723: __write_nocancel (in /lib/tls/libc-2.3.3.so)
     by 0x259AFAD3: __libc_start_main (in /lib/tls/libc-2.3.3.so)
     by 0x8048348: (within /auto/homes/njn25/grind/head4/a.out)
   Address 0x25AB8028 is 0 bytes inside a block of size 10 alloc'd
     at 0x259852B0: malloc (vg_replace_malloc.c:130)
     by 0x80483F1: main (a.c:5)

  Syscall param exit(error_code) contains uninitialised byte(s)
     at 0x25A21B44: __GI__exit (in /lib/tls/libc-2.3.3.so)
     by 0x8048426: main (a.c:8)
]]></programlisting>

<para>... because the program has (a) tried to write uninitialised junk from
the malloc'd block to the standard output, and (b) passed an uninitialised
value to <computeroutput>exit</computeroutput>.  Note that the first error
refers to the memory pointed to by <computeroutput>buf</computeroutput> (not
<computeroutput>buf</computeroutput> itself), but the second error refers to
the argument <computeroutput>error_code</computeroutput> itself.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.overlap" 
       xreflabel="Overlapping source and destination blocks">
<title>Overlapping source and destination blocks</title>

<para>The following C library functions copy some data from one
memory block to another (or something similar):
<computeroutput>memcpy()</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>strcpy()</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>strncpy()</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>strcat()</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>strncat()</computeroutput>. 
The blocks pointed to by their
<computeroutput>src</computeroutput> and
<computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> pointers aren't allowed to
overlap.  Memcheck checks for this.</para>

<para>For example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
==27492== Source and destination overlap in memcpy(0xbffff294, 0xbffff280, 21)
==27492==    at 0x40026CDC: memcpy (mc_replace_strmem.c:71)
==27492==    by 0x804865A: main (overlap.c:40)
==27492== 
]]></programlisting>

<para>You don't want the two blocks to overlap because one of
them could get partially trashed by the copying.</para>

<para>You might think that Memcheck is being overly pedantic reporting
this in the case where <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> is less
than <computeroutput>src</computeroutput>.  For example, the obvious way
to implement <computeroutput>memcpy()</computeroutput> is by copying
from the first byte to the last.  However, the optimisation guides of
some architectures recommend copying from the last byte down to the first.
Also, some implementations of <computeroutput>memcpy()</computeroutput>
zero <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> before copying, because zeroing
the destination's cache line(s) can improve performance.</para>

<para>The moral of the story is:  if you want to write truly portable code,
don't make any assumptions about the language implementation.</para>

</sect2>


</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.suppfiles" xreflabel="Writing suppression files">
<title>Writing suppression files</title>

<para>The basic suppression format is described in 
<xref linkend="manual-core.suppress"/>.</para>

<para>The suppression (2nd) line should have the form:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Memcheck:suppression_type]]></programlisting>

<para>Or, since some of the suppressions are shared with Addrcheck:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Memcheck,Addrcheck:suppression_type]]></programlisting>

<para>The Memcheck suppression types are as follows:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>Value1</computeroutput>, 
    <computeroutput>Value2</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>Value4</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>Value8</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>Value16</computeroutput>,
    meaning an uninitialised-value error when
    using a value of 1, 2, 4, 8 or 16 bytes.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <computeroutput>Cond</computeroutput> (or its old
    name, <computeroutput>Value0</computeroutput>), meaning use
    of an uninitialised CPU condition code.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <computeroutput>Addr1</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>Addr2</computeroutput>, 
    <computeroutput>Addr4</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>Addr8</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>Addr16</computeroutput>, 
    meaning an invalid address during a
    memory access of 1, 2, 4, 8 or 16 bytes respectively.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <computeroutput>Param</computeroutput>, meaning an
    invalid system call parameter error.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <computeroutput>Free</computeroutput>, meaning an
    invalid or mismatching free.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <computeroutput>Overlap</computeroutput>, meaning a
    <computeroutput>src</computeroutput> /
    <computeroutput>dst</computeroutput> overlap in
    <computeroutput>memcpy() or a similar
    function</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Or: <computeroutput>Leak</computeroutput>, meaning
    a memory leak.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>The extra information line: for Param errors, is the name
of the offending system call parameter.  No other error kinds
have this extra line.</para>

<para>The first line of the calling context: for Value and Addr
errors, it is either the name of the function in which the error
occurred, or, failing that, the full path of the .so file or
executable containing the error location.  For Free errors, is
the name of the function doing the freeing (eg,
<computeroutput>free</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>__builtin_vec_delete</computeroutput>, etc).  For
Overlap errors, is the name of the function with the overlapping
arguments (eg.  <computeroutput>memcpy()</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>strcpy()</computeroutput>, etc).</para>

<para>Lastly, there's the rest of the calling context.</para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.machine" 
       xreflabel="Details of Memcheck's checking machinery">
<title>Details of Memcheck's checking machinery</title>

<para>Read this section if you want to know, in detail, exactly
what and how Memcheck is checking.</para>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.value" xreflabel="Valid-value (V) bit">
<title>Valid-value (V) bits</title>

<para>It is simplest to think of Memcheck implementing a
synthetic CPU which is identical to a real CPU, except
for one crucial detail.  Every bit (literally) of data processed,
stored and handled by the real CPU has, in the synthetic CPU, an
associated "valid-value" bit, which says whether or not the
accompanying bit has a legitimate value.  In the discussions
which follow, this bit is referred to as the V (valid-value)
bit.</para>

<para>Each byte in the system therefore has a 8 V bits which
follow it wherever it goes.  For example, when the CPU loads a
word-size item (4 bytes) from memory, it also loads the
corresponding 32 V bits from a bitmap which stores the V bits for
the process' entire address space.  If the CPU should later write
the whole or some part of that value to memory at a different
address, the relevant V bits will be stored back in the V-bit
bitmap.</para>

<para>In short, each bit in the system has an associated V bit,
which follows it around everywhere, even inside the CPU.  Yes,
all the CPU's registers (integer, floating point, and condition 
registers) have their own V bit vectors.</para>

<para>Copying values around does not cause Memcheck to check for,
or report on, errors.  However, when a value is used in a way
which might conceivably affect the outcome of your program's
computation, the associated V bits are immediately checked.  If
any of these indicate that the value is undefined, an error is
reported.</para>

<para>Here's an (admittedly nonsensical) example:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
int i, j;
int a[10], b[10];
for ( i = 0; i < 10; i++ ) {
  j = a[i];
  b[i] = j;
}]]></programlisting>

<para>Memcheck emits no complaints about this, since it merely
copies uninitialised values from
<computeroutput>a[]</computeroutput> into
<computeroutput>b[]</computeroutput>, and doesn't use them in any
way.  However, if the loop is changed to:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
for ( i = 0; i < 10; i++ ) {
  j += a[i];
}
if ( j == 77 ) 
  printf("hello there\n");
]]></programlisting>

<para>then Valgrind will complain, at the
<computeroutput>if</computeroutput>, that the condition depends
on uninitialised values.  Note that it <command>doesn't</command>
complain at the <computeroutput>j += a[i];</computeroutput>,
since at that point the undefinedness is not "observable".  It's
only when a decision has to be made as to whether or not to do
the <computeroutput>printf</computeroutput> -- an observable
action of your program -- that Memcheck complains.</para>

<para>Most low level operations, such as adds, cause Memcheck to
use the V bits for the operands to calculate the V bits for the result.
Even if the result is partially or wholly undefined, it does not
complain.</para>

<para>Checks on definedness only occur in three places: when a
value is used to generate a memory address, when control
flow decision needs to be made, and when a system call is
detected, Valgrind checks definedness of parameters as
required.</para>

<para>If a check should detect undefinedness, an error message is
issued.  The resulting value is subsequently regarded as
well-defined.  To do otherwise would give long chains of error
messages.  In effect, we say that undefined values are
non-infectious.</para>

<para>This sounds overcomplicated.  Why not just check all reads
from memory, and complain if an undefined value is loaded into a
CPU register?  Well, that doesn't work well, because perfectly
legitimate C programs routinely copy uninitialised values around
in memory, and we don't want endless complaints about that.
Here's the canonical example.  Consider a struct like
this:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
struct S { int x; char c; };
struct S s1, s2;
s1.x = 42;
s1.c = 'z';
s2 = s1;
]]></programlisting>

<para>The question to ask is: how large is <computeroutput>struct
S</computeroutput>, in bytes?  An
<computeroutput>int</computeroutput> is 4 bytes and a
<computeroutput>char</computeroutput> one byte, so perhaps a
<computeroutput>struct S</computeroutput> occupies 5 bytes?
Wrong.  All (non-toy) compilers we know of will round the size of
<computeroutput>struct S</computeroutput> up to a whole number of
words, in this case 8 bytes.  Not doing this forces compilers to
generate truly appalling code for subscripting arrays of
<computeroutput>struct S</computeroutput>'s.</para>

<para>So <computeroutput>s1</computeroutput> occupies 8 bytes,
yet only 5 of them will be initialised.  For the assignment
<computeroutput>s2 = s1</computeroutput>, gcc generates code to
copy all 8 bytes wholesale into
<computeroutput>s2</computeroutput> without regard for their
meaning.  If Memcheck simply checked values as they came out of
memory, it would yelp every time a structure assignment like this
happened.  So the more complicated semantics described above is
necessary.  This allows <literal>gcc</literal> to copy
<computeroutput>s1</computeroutput> into
<computeroutput>s2</computeroutput> any way it likes, and a
warning will only be emitted if the uninitialised values are
later used.</para>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.vaddress" xreflabel=" Valid-address (A) bits">
<title>Valid-address (A) bits</title>

<para>Notice that the previous subsection describes how the
validity of values is established and maintained without having
to say whether the program does or does not have the right to
access any particular memory location.  We now consider the
latter issue.</para>

<para>As described above, every bit in memory or in the CPU has
an associated valid-value (V) bit.  In
addition, all bytes in memory, but not in the CPU, have an
associated valid-address (A) bit.  This
indicates whether or not the program can legitimately read or
write that location.  It does not give any indication of the
validity or the data at that location -- that's the job of the
V bits -- only whether or not the location may
be accessed.</para>

<para>Every time your program reads or writes memory, Memcheck
checks the A bits associated with the address.
If any of them indicate an invalid address, an error is emitted.
Note that the reads and writes themselves do not change the A
bits, only consult them.</para>

<para>So how do the A bits get set/cleared?  Like this:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>When the program starts, all the global data areas are
    marked as accessible.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When the program does malloc/new, the A bits for
    exactly the area allocated, and not a byte more, are marked
    as accessible.  Upon freeing the area the A bits are changed
    to indicate inaccessibility.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When the stack pointer register
    (<literal>SP</literal>) moves up or down,
    <literal>A</literal> bits are set.  The rule is that the area
    from <literal>SP</literal> up to the base of the stack is
    marked as accessible, and below <literal>SP</literal> is
    inaccessible.  (If that sounds illogical, bear in mind that
    the stack grows down, not up, on almost all Unix systems,
    including GNU/Linux.)  Tracking <literal>SP</literal> like
    this has the useful side-effect that the section of stack
    used by a function for local variables etc is automatically
    marked accessible on function entry and inaccessible on
    exit.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When doing system calls, A bits are changed
    appropriately.  For example, mmap() magically makes files
    appear in the process's address space, so the A bits must be
    updated if mmap() succeeds.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>Optionally, your program can tell Valgrind about such
    changes explicitly, using the client request mechanism
    described above.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>


<sect2 id="mc-manual.together" xreflabel="Putting it all together">
<title>Putting it all together</title>

<para>Memcheck's checking machinery can be summarised as
follows:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Each byte in memory has 8 associated
    V (valid-value) bits, saying whether or
    not the byte has a defined value, and a single
    A (valid-address) bit, saying whether or
    not the program currently has the right to read/write that
    address.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When memory is read or written, the relevant
    A bits are consulted.  If they indicate an
    invalid address, Valgrind emits an Invalid read or Invalid
    write error.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When memory is read into the CPU's registers,
    the relevant V bits are fetched from
    memory and stored in the simulated CPU.  They are not
    consulted.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When a register is written out to memory, the
    V bits for that register are written back
    to memory too.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When values in CPU registers are used to
    generate a memory address, or to determine the outcome of a
    conditional branch, the V bits for those
    values are checked, and an error emitted if any of them are
    undefined.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When values in CPU registers are used for any
    other purpose, Valgrind computes the V bits for the result,
    but does not check them.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>One the V bits for a value in the
    CPU have been checked, they are then set to indicate
    validity.  This avoids long chains of errors.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>When values are loaded from memory, valgrind checks the
    A bits for that location and issues an illegal-address
    warning if needed.  In that case, the V bits loaded are
    forced to indicate Valid, despite the location being invalid.</para>
    <para>This apparently strange choice reduces the amount of
    confusing information presented to the user.  It avoids the
    unpleasant phenomenon in which memory is read from a place
    which is both unaddressible and contains invalid values, and,
    as a result, you get not only an invalid-address (read/write)
    error, but also a potentially large set of
    uninitialised-value errors, one for every time the value is
    used.</para>
    <para>There is a hazy boundary case to do with multi-byte
    loads from addresses which are partially valid and partially
    invalid.  See details of the flag
    <computeroutput>--partial-loads-ok</computeroutput> for
    details.  </para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>


<para>Memcheck intercepts calls to malloc, calloc, realloc,
valloc, memalign, free, new and delete.  The behaviour you get
is:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>malloc/new: the returned memory is marked as
    addressible but not having valid values.  This means you have
    to write on it before you can read it.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>calloc: returned memory is marked both addressible and
    valid, since calloc() clears the area to zero.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>realloc: if the new size is larger than the old, the
    new section is addressible but invalid, as with
    malloc.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>If the new size is smaller, the dropped-off section is
    marked as unaddressible.  You may only pass to realloc a
    pointer previously issued to you by malloc/calloc/realloc.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>free/delete: you may only pass to free a pointer
    previously issued to you by malloc/calloc/realloc, or the
    value NULL. Otherwise, Valgrind complains.  If the pointer is
    indeed valid, Valgrind marks the entire area it points at as
    unaddressible, and places the block in the
    freed-blocks-queue.  The aim is to defer as long as possible
    reallocation of this block.  Until that happens, all attempts
    to access it will elicit an invalid-address error, as you
    would hope.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>



<sect1 id="mc-manual.leaks" xreflabel="Memory leak detection">
<title>Memory leak detection</title>

<para>Memcheck keeps track of all memory blocks issued in
response to calls to malloc/calloc/realloc/new.  So when the
program exits, it knows which blocks are still outstanding --
have not been returned, in other words.  Ideally, you want your
program to have no blocks still in use at exit.  But many
programs do.</para>

<para>For each such block, Memcheck scans the entire address
space of the process, looking for pointers to the block.  One of
three situations may result:</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para>A pointer to the start of the block is found.  This
    usually indicates programming sloppiness; since the block is
    still pointed at, the programmer could, at least in
    principle, free'd it before program exit.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>A pointer to the interior of the block is found.  The
    pointer might originally have pointed to the start and have
    been moved along, or it might be entirely unrelated.
    Memcheck deems such a block as "dubious", that is, possibly
    leaked, because it's unclear whether or not a pointer to it
    still exists.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>The worst outcome is that no pointer to the block can
    be found.  The block is classified as "leaked", because the
    programmer could not possibly have free'd it at program exit,
    since no pointer to it exists.  This might be a symptom of
    having lost the pointer at some earlier point in the
    program.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>Memcheck reports summaries about leaked and dubious blocks.
For each such block, it will also tell you where the block was
allocated.  This should help you figure out why the pointer to it
has been lost.  In general, you should attempt to ensure your
programs do not have any leaked or dubious blocks at exit.</para>

<para>The precise area of memory in which Memcheck searches for
pointers is: all naturally-aligned 4-byte words for which all A
bits indicate addressibility and all V bits indicated that the
stored value is actually valid.</para>

</sect1>


<sect1 id="mc-manual.clientreqs" xreflabel="Client requests">
<title>Client Requests</title>

<para>The following client requests are defined in
<filename>memcheck.h</filename>.  They also work for Addrcheck.
See <filename>memcheck.h</filename> for exact details of their
arguments.</para>

<itemizedlist>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_MAKE_NOACCESS</computeroutput>,
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_MAKE_WRITABLE</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_MAKE_READABLE</computeroutput>.
    These mark address ranges as completely inaccessible,
    accessible but containing undefined data, and accessible and
    containing defined data, respectively.  Subsequent errors may
    have their faulting addresses described in terms of these
    blocks.  Returns a "block handle".  Returns zero when not run
    on Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_DISCARD</computeroutput>: At
    some point you may want Valgrind to stop reporting errors in
    terms of the blocks defined by the previous three macros.  To
    do this, the above macros return a small-integer "block
    handle".  You can pass this block handle to
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_DISCARD</computeroutput>.  After
    doing so, Valgrind will no longer be able to relate
    addressing errors to the user-defined block associated with
    the handle.  The permissions settings associated with the
    handle remain in place; this just affects how errors are
    reported, not whether they are reported.  Returns 1 for an
    invalid handle and 0 for a valid handle (although passing
    invalid handles is harmless).  Always returns 0 when not run
    on Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_CHECK_WRITABLE</computeroutput>
    and <computeroutput>VALGRIND_CHECK_READABLE</computeroutput>:
    check immediately whether or not the given address range has
    the relevant property, and if not, print an error message.
    Also, for the convenience of the client, returns zero if the
    relevant property holds; otherwise, the returned value is the
    address of the first byte for which the property is not true.
    Always returns 0 when not run on Valgrind.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_CHECK_DEFINED</computeroutput>:
    a quick and easy way to find out whether Valgrind thinks a
    particular variable (lvalue, to be precise) is addressible
    and defined.  Prints an error message if not.  Returns no
    value.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_DO_LEAK_CHECK</computeroutput>:
    run the memory leak detector right now.  Returns no value.  I
    guess this could be used to incrementally check for leaks
    between arbitrary places in the program's execution.
    Warning: not properly tested!</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_COUNT_LEAKS</computeroutput>:
    fills in the four arguments with the number of bytes of
    memory found by the previous leak check to be leaked,
    dubious, reachable and suppressed.  Again, useful in test
    harness code, after calling
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_DO_LEAK_CHECK</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para><computeroutput>VALGRIND_GET_VBITS</computeroutput> and
    <computeroutput>VALGRIND_SET_VBITS</computeroutput>: allow
    you to get and set the V (validity) bits for an address
    range.  You should probably only set V bits that you have got
    with <computeroutput>VALGRIND_GET_VBITS</computeroutput>.
    Only for those who really know what they are doing.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
</chapter>
